<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mappe of Moses: or, a guide for governours Two sermons lately preached before the iudges of assize, and magistrates of the towne of Reding, at two seuerall assemblies there held for the countie of Berk. By Theophilus Taylor, Master of Arts, and pastor of the parish of S. Laurence in Reding.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Theophilus, d. 1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23819</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103237</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838994</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838994</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3387</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13527)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1222:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mappe of Moses: or, a guide for governours Two sermons lately preached before the iudges of assize, and magistrates of the towne of Reding, at two seuerall assemblies there held for the countie of Berk. By Theophilus Taylor, Master of Arts, and pastor of the parish of S. Laurence in Reding.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Theophilus, d. 1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 50 p. : folding table  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Duties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3387:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Mappe of Moſes:</hi> OR, A GVIDE FOR GOVERNOVRS.</p>
            <p>Two Sermons lately Preached before the Iudges of Aſſize, and Magiſtrates of the Towne of <hi>Reding,</hi> at two ſeuerall aſſemblies there held for the Countie of <hi>Berk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THEOPHILVS TAYLOR, Maſter of Arts, and Paſtor of the Pariſh of <hi>S. Laurence</hi> in <hi>Reding.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROVERBS 20.6.</hi>
               </bibl> Many men will boaſt euery one of his owne goodneſſe; but who can finde a faithfull man?</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by THOMAS HARPER. 1629.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3387:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3387:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE Knight, Sir <hi>Iohn Mounſon,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bathe,</hi> Sonne and Heire to the Right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>Thomas Mounſon</hi> of <hi>Burton</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> Knight and Baronet: the Author wiſheth increaſe of grace here, and glory hereafter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Sir: Sithence the ſmalleſt tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates in this age paſſe not without their Dedicatories; I would not ſeem ſingular in denying this little Booke that ordinary priuiledge; which being but newly hatcht, doth (with the Philoſophers bird, which flew into his boſome) ſeek ſhelter vnder your Worſhips co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerture; whoſe name I durſt not prefixe before ſo weake a worke, but that I haue ſome encouragements: as firſt, the inward familiarity which once I had with you for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers yeeres together in your tender age. Againe, your loue to learning, and that affection you haue alwaies ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards them that leane that way: moreouer, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious reſpect which you haue alwaies teſtified to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of truth, one maine branch whereof is briefly laid downe in this Treatiſe; and laſtly, thoſe employments whereunto you are ſometimes called, by reaſon of your place of Iuſtice-ſhip; vnto the faithfull diſcharge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, this little (Mappe of <hi>Moſes</hi>) will afford you ſome
<pb facs="tcp:3387:3"/> direction. I dare not (for feare of flattery) blaze the leaſt part of that commendation which a worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of your acquaintance hath giuen you in his Booke dedicated vnto you,<note place="margin">M. <hi>Tho. Ganif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> I ſquire p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>16.</note> and intituled, <hi>The Secretaries Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et I m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y boldly affirme that that generous toward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which he with others at that time diſcerned in you, was but as a dram in compariſon of that weight of worth which is now found in you: which as it is no little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto your godly and worthy Parents, whoſe earneſt deſire alwaies was to giue you their <hi>Lemuel,</hi> a truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and generous education: ſo it hath much reioyced me to heare the relation both of your religious loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, as alſo of the affection of your Country to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, teſtified ſufficiently in their late nomination and election of you for one of their Knights in the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament. Now Sir, as for this poore tractate, I humbly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your Worſhip to accept<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, as a certaine teſtimony of my thankefull minde, <hi>qui, ſi non potui maxima; parua dedi:</hi> ſuch as I haue I preſent vnto you; a few blotted leaues, wherein you ſhall not meete with any flouriſhing words, or curious lines; yet with Gods truth euidently laid downe in the plaineſt dialect; in acceptance wherof, I ſhal not be wanting in my prayers, for Gods bleſsing vpon your ſelfe, and your vertuous Lady, that your houſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour may continue vnblemiſhed.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—donec fluctus formica marinos</l>
               <l>Ebibat, &amp; totum teſtudo perambulet orbem;</l>
            </q>
            <p>That God may direct you in all your proceedings, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in you his ſauing graces; bleſſe you and all yours with long life, and much happineſſe, to his glory, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good, your owne comfort here, and eternall glory hereafter; in hope and full perſwaſion whereof, I humbly take my leaue, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all obſeruance, THEOPHILVS TAYLOR.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3387:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:3387:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:3387:4"/>
            <head>HEBREWES III. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERSE V. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>The dependance, <hi>wherein Chriſt is ſet foorth</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Poſitiuely,</hi> in the 1. and 2. chapter, page 1.</item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Comparatiuely,</hi> in 3. chapter, 2. v page 2.</item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Tranſcendently,</hi> 3. chap. 3. v. page 3.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Subſtance, <hi>wherein two parts</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Subiect</hi> (Moſes) wherein three things,
<list>
                              <item>1. <hi>Expoſition,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is deſcribed what Moſes was, 4.
<list>
                                    <item>1. By his country and nation, 4.</item>
                                    <item>2. By his diſcent.</item>
                                    <item>3. By his parentage.</item>
                                    <item>4. By his viſage.</item>
                                    <item>5. By his function and office three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
<list>
                                          <item>1. Propheticall, 4.</item>
                                          <item>2. Sac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                                <desc>•</desc>
                                             </gap>rdotic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                                <desc>•</desc>
                                             </gap>ll, 4.</item>
                                          <item>3. Iudiciall, 5.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. <hi>Obſeruation,</hi> viz. Secular iuriſdiction is of Gods ordination, 5.
<list>
                                    <item>Reaſons are two in regard of
<list>
                                          <item>1. generall reformation, 6.</item>
                                          <item>2. generall conſeruation, 7</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>3. <hi>Application,</hi> two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, of
<list>
                                    <item>1. Confutation of Anabaptiſts, 8.</item>
                                    <item>2. Inſtruction teaching vs
<list>
                                          <item>1. to repaire vnto them, 12.</item>
                                          <item>2. to honour them, 15.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Predicate,</hi> (faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full) wherein foure things,
<list>
                              <item>1. <hi>Expoſition,</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>1. In what ſence he was faithfull, 19.</item>
                                    <item>2. In whoſe houſe he was faithfull, 20.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. <hi>Illuſtration,</hi> It appeares that he was faithfull, by his
<list>
                                    <item>Adaptation being fitted thereunto two wayes,
<list>
                                          <item>1. By his ſcience: both in things
<list>
                                                <item>1. humane, 21.</item>
                                                <item>2. diuine, 2.</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                          <item>2. By his conſcience, 24.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Execution of his office being faithfull
<list>
                                          <item>1. <hi>Deo,</hi> to God, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing by his 25
<list>
                                                <item>1. faith in God, 95.</item>
                                                <item>3. pi ty towards God, 25.</item>
                                                <item>3. zeale for God, 26.</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                          <item>2. <hi>Sacerdoti,</hi> to the Prieſt in three things
<list>
                                                <item>1. <hi>deprecando,</hi> in begging pardon for them, 27.</item>
                                                <item>2. <hi>dirigendo,</hi> directing him what to doe, 27.</item>
                                                <item>3. <hi>amplexando,</hi> in embracing him, 28.</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                          <item>3. <hi>Populo,</hi> to the people, and that in 3. things
<list>
                                                <item>1. <hi>diligentia,</hi> by his diligence for them, 29.</item>
                                                <item>2. <hi>dilectione,</hi> by his loue towards them, 31.</item>
                                                <item>3. <hi>iuſtitia,</hi> by doing of iuſtice among them which muſt be
<list>
                                                      <item>1. complete, 39.</item>
                                                      <item>2. generall, 41.</item>
                                                      <item>3. voluntary, 42.</item>
                                                      <item>4. deliberate, 42.</item>
                                                      <item>5. ſtable, 43.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>3. <hi>Obſeruation,</hi> viz. All that are in Moſes place muſt be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as he was, 43.
<list>
                                    <item>Reaſons are two, being drawne
<list>
                                          <item>1. <hi>A pari,</hi> 43.</item>
                                          <item>2. <hi>A periculo,</hi> 44.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>4. <hi>Application,</hi> wherein two things
<list>
                                    <item>1. The perſons to whom it is applied 45
<list>
                                          <item>1. Iudges.</item>
                                          <item>2. Counſellours.</item>
                                          <item>3. Miniſters.</item>
                                          <item>4. Iurors.</item>
                                          <item>5. Officers.</item>
                                          <item>6. Witneſſes.</item>
                                          <item>7. All men.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>2. The motiues by which it is enforced, are foure
<list>
                                          <item>1. Gods preſidence, 48.</item>
                                          <item>2. Gods obſeruance, 49.</item>
                                          <item>3. Gods indulgence, 49.</item>
                                          <item>4. Gods recompence, 50.</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Place this Table after the Epiſtle, before Page</hi> 1.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3387:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3387:5"/>
            <head>THE MAPPE OF <hi>MOSES.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>HEBR. Chap. 3. Verſ. 5.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>verily was faithfull.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll Scripture is written for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by holy men diuinely inſpired for that purpoſe, whereof as <hi>Moſes</hi> mentioned in my Text was the firſt writer; in the opinion of<note n="a" place="margin">Euſeb. lib. c. <hi>21</hi> de praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Evangel. Primus apud H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>raeos ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ille Theologus Moyſes, ſcripta reliquit.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Moſes</hi> was the firſt H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n-man of Scripture, (and therefore much more ancient than any Greeke Writer whomſoeuer) witneſſe both<note n="b" place="margin">Sanct. Iuſtin. in admon. ad gent. M yſes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am hiſtoriam Hebraicè ſcripſit cum Graecerum literae nondu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſſent inventae.</note> 
               <hi>Sanctus Iuſtinus;</hi> whoſe words are theſe: The Hiſtory of <hi>Moſes</hi> was perfected ere any Greeke letter was inuented: and<note n="c" place="margin">Phil. Iud. de vita Morſit. Moyſes p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it &amp; an iqutor, non tantum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aeciae ſapientibus, ſed etiam omnibus qui apud Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos aliquid ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt.</note> 
               <hi>Philo Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeus,</hi> who ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> writ his Hebrew Hiſtory, ere Greece harboured any famous Philoſopher, or any other learned Author So he was the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>geſt, as appeareth both by that great volume of the Pentatouch, by the Booke of <hi>Iob,</hi> and that of the<note n="d" place="margin">Fabricius in <hi>90.</hi> Pſal. liber Pſalmorum Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidi inſcribitur non quidem quòd ille omnium ſit author: ſed quòd plurimorum. <hi>106. Pſalme.</hi> Paraeus in loc. Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t architectus permiſſimus pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo fundamenta ponit poſtea pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietes imponit &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mum conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, ita Apoſtolus. <hi>Hebrewes 1.3. Hebr. 2.16. Hebr. 3.1.</hi>
               </note> Pſalmes, of ſome whereof hee was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
            <p>Now as in this mans writings many vſefull documents are propounded vnto vs for our inſtruction, declaring what things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re to be beleeued, what things are to be practiſed, and what to be hoped for: ſo many things are alſo recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him, both by the Prophets before Chriſt (as <hi>Dauid</hi>)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3387:6"/> by Chriſt himſelfe who followed the Prophets, and by the Apoſtles who followed Chriſt; eſpecially Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in this Chapter, who being deſirous to magnifie Chriſt to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt eleuation, (not vnlike a skilfull Architector) who firſt layeth the foundation, then reareth the walles, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards couereth the roofe of the houſe: So our Apoſtle in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting of Chriſt, he declareth what he is:</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Poſitiuely,</hi> (ſo laying the foundation) in the firſt and ſecond chapter, deſcribing him partly by his perſon, and partly by his office.</p>
            <p n="1">1 By his Perſon:
<list>
                  <item>1 God, that he is the brightneſſe of glory.</item>
                  <item>2 Man, that hee tooke not the Angelicall nature, but the ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 By his office in the firſt verſe of this Chapter, where Chriſt is called the Apoſtle and high Prieſt of our profeſſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Comparatiuely,</hi> (ſo rearing the wals) comparing him with <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man much reſpected and honoured among the Hebrewes,<note place="margin">Iohn 9.28. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> writ this Epiſtle, as they doe intimate in their ſpeech vnto the blinde man reſtored to his ſight: <hi>We are the Diſciples of Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt is compared vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> in many things: each of them,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Irefully alike perſecuted; both
<list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 1. Math. 2.</note>1 About the ſame time, when both of them were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants and in ſwadling clouts.</item>
                  <item>2 By inſtruments of the like ranke and quality; <hi>Moſes</hi> by <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of Egypt, and Chriſt by <hi>Herod</hi> King of the Iewes</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Exod. 2.9.</note>2 Miraculouſly alike preſerued: <hi>Moſes</hi> by her whoſe ſonne he was called, namely <hi>Thermutis</hi> the daughter of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh:</hi> who ſaid to his owne mother: <hi>take this childe away and nurſe him for me, and I will reward thee:</hi> and Chriſt by <hi>Ioſeph</hi> whoſe ſonne he was called,<note place="margin">Math 2.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Numb. 12. 1. Math. 11.29: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> though onely ſo ſuppoſed: <hi>he tooke the Babe and went into Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Affably alike diſpoſed: <hi>Moſes was a very meeke man aboue all them that were on the earth;</hi> and ſo Chriſt, <hi>I am meeke and lowly in heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3387:6"/>4 Louingly alike affianced and eſpouſed:<note place="margin">Exod. 2.19.21.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> married <hi>Zipporah</hi> the daughter of <hi>Iethro</hi> the Ethiopian, and therefore blacke, yet fruitfull, for ſhe bare vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> two ſons,<note place="margin">Exod. 18.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhon</hi> and <hi>Eleaſer:</hi> ſo Chriſt hath affianced himſelfe to the Church; who if ſhe want externall formoſity,<note place="margin">Nigra at fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuoſa.</note> yet not fecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, for ſhe bringeth forth many children vnto God.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Faithfully alike imployed in office and function: <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was a Steward or Gouernour ouer the ancient Iſraelites, who were called Gods people and houſhold;<note place="margin">Math. 28.18.</note> ſo Chriſt hee hath the gouernment of the Church, vnto whom as all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is giuen vnto him in heauen, ſo alſo in earth.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Tranſcendently,</hi> (ſo couering the roofe) he maketh Chriſt to excell <hi>Moſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 1.4.</note> and indeede ſeeing that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> preferreth Chriſt before the Angels, who are creatures not corruptible, for they dye not, nor culpable, for they ſinne not, as doth euery man; it is then no maruell that compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him with <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man both mortall and ſinfull,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Paraeus in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</p>
                  <p>Domus profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milia in domo. <hi>1</hi> Poteſtate.</p>
               </note> hee giue Chriſt preheminence ouer <hi>Moſes,</hi> as he doth, and that in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In authority and power, 3. and 4. verſes, <hi>hee that is the owner and builder of the houſe, hath greater honour then the houſe:</hi> that is (by a Synecdoche) then the houſhold, or any there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: ſo Chriſt our Sauiour, the builder and owner of the Church, hath more honour and power then <hi>Moſes,</hi> who though a Steward in, yet but a member of the houſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In Fidelity, <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithfull in many things,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Fidelitate. <hi>Ioh. 4.26.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Moyſos fuit fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis ut famulus, at Chriſtus ut fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius. <hi>Subſtance.</hi>
               </note> but yet in ſome things failing (as you ſhall here hereafter) but Chriſt was faithfull in his offices without any deficiency whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, <hi>which of you can accuſe me of ſinne:</hi> againe, <hi>Moſes was faithfull as a Seruant, but Chriſt was faithfull as a ſonne:</hi> And thus much for the dependance.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſubſtance of the words comprehendeth two parts, <hi>1</hi> the ſubiect, <hi>Moſes; 2</hi> the predicate, <hi>Faithfull.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1 Subiect, <hi>Moſes,</hi> wherein three things are to be handled, 1 <hi>Expoſition,</hi> 2 <hi>Obſeruation,</hi> 3 <hi>Application.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 Expoſition, who this <hi>Moſes</hi> was, who is deſcribed in Scripture diuerſly.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3387:7"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Exod. 2.6. Exod. 2.1. Numb. 16.29. Hebr. 11.23.</hi> Ioſephus erat hic infans tam ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s, ut aſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entium oculos in ſe raperet.</p>
                     <p>Theop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>. dicit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unc pucrum blande ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e &amp; ob id ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſuiſſe, in <hi>Heb. 11.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Phil. Huiaſmodi f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t vita ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Moyſis regis, legis latoris, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; pontificis. <hi>1 Propheticall. Numb. 2.6.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Greg Quanto mundus ad e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitatem du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nto nobis aeternae ſcentiae a litus largins <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deut. 34.10.</hi> Aqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt. <hi>174.</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. <hi>4.</hi> Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad viſionum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tatem, &amp; miraculorum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>perationem.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>2 Sacerdoticall. Pſal. 99.23. 1</hi> O atio. <hi>P al 99.6.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. &amp; Iun. niſi conſtituſſet Moyſes in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione <hi>(1)</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                           <desc>•••••</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>6.22.</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>io.</p>
                  </note>1 By his Country or Nation (an Hebrew.)</p>
               <p n="2">2 By deſcent or lineage: of the houſe of <hi>Leui:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 By his parentage, his Fathers name was <hi>Amram,</hi> his Mothers <hi>Iochebed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 By his viſage he was faire: <hi>Theophilact</hi> ſaith, that when as he ſhould haue been murthered with the reſt of the Hebrew children, ſuch was his extraordinary beauty and comelineſſe, and with ſo ſweet and ſmiling countenance hee beheld the tormentors, as that they were enforced to ſpare him, though they had a ſtrait mandate to the contrary.</p>
               <p n="5">5 And laſtly, by his office and function: <hi>Moſes</hi> liued 120. yeares: of which time he liued</p>
               <p n="1">1 A Courtier in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court 40. yeeres.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A ſhepheard in Midian other forty yeeres.</p>
               <p n="3">3 A Gouernour in the deſart the laſt 40 yeeres, in which quadragenary he did execute a threefold office.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Propheticall,</hi> 2 <hi>Sacerdoticall,</hi> 3 <hi>Iudiciall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Propheticall, Moſes</hi> was a Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>I will ſpeake mouth to mouth:</hi> and againe, <hi>there aroſe not a Prophet ſince in Iſrael like vnto Moſes:</hi> Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> obſerueth that of later times there haue beene men of as great, if not of greater note, then <hi>Moſes:</hi> as <hi>Dauid,</hi> who was wiſer than his ancients, or then his teachers; and <hi>Salomon,</hi> who was wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer than any man: and withall, he giues this reaſon: By how much the world is nearer to the expiration, ſo much the more is his gift of illumination: yet (as <hi>Aquinas</hi> noteth) if we conſider <hi>Moſes</hi> in his admirable viſions, for to whom did God ſpeake face to face? or in his extraordinary miracles; few Prophets can be compared vnto him.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Sacerdoticall; Moſes</hi> was a Prieſt, who was both num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among them, as alſo did performe the offices of them. There were three ſpeciall actions enioyned the Prieſts.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Supplication, they were to pray for the people; ſo <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> when God was minded to deſtroy Iſrael. <hi>Moſes</hi> did ſtand vp in the gap, deprecating againſt their puniſhment.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Vnction, they were to annoint with oyle: ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auing annoynted the Tabernacle, the Altar, and the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3387:7"/> Inſtruments: <hi>he poured the annoynting oyle vpon Aaron,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 8.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and annoynted him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 Oblation; they were to ſacrifice for the people;<note place="margin">3 <hi>Sacrificatio.</hi> Hebr 11.28. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Queſt. Sol.</note> ſo did <hi>Moſes: he prepared the Paſſeouer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why doth <hi>Moſes</hi> meddle with the Prieſts office, whereunto his elder brother was called?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol. Moſes</hi> in his Sacerdoticall actions did much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from <hi>Aaron:</hi> For,</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Aaron</hi> was by Gods appointment annoynted vnto his Prieſthood: <hi>Moſes</hi> not at all annoynted.<note place="margin">Dion Carth. in quaeſt. in Leuit. In Moyſe vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fuiſſe pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo ſpiritualis poteſtatis &amp; ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularis ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum exigentiam ſtatus plebis illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Aaron</hi> was an ordinary Prieſt, but <hi>Moſes</hi> was extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary: <hi>Moſes fuit ſacerdos ſecundum ſpeciale priuilegium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Aaron</hi> had many ſucceſſors in his order of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, but <hi>Moſes</hi> had none to ſucceede him.</p>
               <p>Wherefore (moſt likely it is) that <hi>Moſes</hi> would not haue intereſted himſelfe in this office, but that he receiued ſome ſpeciall direction for the vndertaking thereof, and withall perceiued, that the neceſſity of thoſe times did require the ſame, and moſt euident it is, that <hi>Moſes</hi> did not execute this office after the time of <hi>Aarons</hi> conſecration: but when <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> was admitted, <hi>Moſes</hi> is diſcharged.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Iudiciall:</hi> he was a Ruler, Iudge, and Lawgiuer:<note place="margin">3 Iudiciall.</note> which title and office, (though ſome of the Hebrewes denied him) <hi>who made thee a man of authority, and a Iudge ouer vs?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod. 2.14.</hi> Tolet annot. in <hi>12.</hi> Luc. Moyſes cum haec ageret nondum erat princeps ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, iudex.</note> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogation being a plaine negation; for that at this time he had no place of Iudicature or gouernement, which may ſafely be concluded from his flight into the land of Midian; which long and weariſome iourney he might haue auoided, if he had beene abſolutely authoriſed: yet afterwards hee was called to the office of a Ruler, and did ſit and iudge the people: and of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſet vp by Almighty God in this office, we are to ſpeake, and from thence proceed to the ſecond generall thing propounded, viz. the Obſeruation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſeruation, viz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obſeruation.</note> Secular Iuriſdiction is of Gods ordination<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that the powers that be,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> are ordained of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3387:8"/> God.<note place="margin">Hic eſt egregius Reip. ordo ut alij imperent, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lij obtemperent. <hi>Deut. 16.18.</hi> Judices &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratores conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuito tibi in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> portis tuis. Pet. Mart. lib. Ind. c. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>1.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Iudaeorum fuit melior ſub. Iudicibus quàm ſub Regibus. <hi>1 Reaſon. Philem. 11.</hi> Adoleſcentes magis me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> quam ratione revocantur a vitijs. Ambr. <hi>Iob. 19.16.</hi>
                  </note> The Lord will not ſuffer the Iewes at any time to be without ſome kind of gouernou s; at the firſt he gouerned them by a Patriarchicall gouernment, till the time of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> then by a Iudiciall gouernment of Iudges vntill <hi>Saul,</hi> vnder which kinde of gouernment the Iewes had, much peace and happineſſe; afterwards by a Regall power of Kings, which continuated till the captiuity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons declaring the neceſſity thereof are two.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>In regard of generall reformation:</hi> if no gouernment, then no puniſhment; if no puniſhment, then man (whoſe imaginations are onely euill) would become impetuous, violent, turbulent: if no magiſtracy, you ſhould ſee a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ataxy and diſorder in all eſtates.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In your families, your ſeruants riotous, as ſomtimes <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> contemptuous as they whom <hi>Iob</hi> entertained, whom when he called they did ſcorne to anſwere; your children proue <hi>Ben-onies,</hi> ſuch as through their audacity and luxury would in ſhort time bring your gray heades with ſorrow to the graue, which Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> well obſerued when he ſaid, that terrour is more preualent to draw youth from vice then fauour.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In the Church ſuch abuſes as would cauſe you to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the ſervice of the Lord;<note place="margin">1 Kings 12.31.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> the baſeſt and vnworthieſt of men ſeruing at the Altar, as in the dayes of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> and the moſt loathſome dogs and ſwine without reuerence or repentance ſate at the Altar eating and drinking their owne damnation.<note place="margin">1 Cor 11.29.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 In the common wealth ſuch a racket as would vexe your righteous ſoules; the hand of maleuolent <hi>Iſmael</hi> lifted vp againſt his neighbor; the ſword of bloudy <hi>Cain</hi> ſheathed in the bowels of his brother; the hedges and high wayes like vnto the rode betwixt <hi>Iericho</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caſſiod. Iura publica certiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſunt humanae vitae ſolatia, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmorum auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, impiorum fraena.</note> a hiue and harbour for the vagabond thiefe and robber; the open ſtreete a ſtage and theatre for the obſcene <hi>(and vnſeene)</hi> adulterer; (in a word) the whole common wealth out of order, and the whole earth groaning vnder the burthen of the ſinfull offender.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3387:8"/>2 <hi>In regard of the conſeruation</hi> of the whole politique body; what the head is vnto the body naturall,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2 Reaſon.</hi> Regnum ſine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge eſt corpus ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne capi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſt. Quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine corpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſic <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge civitas.</note> that is a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to the body politicall: a body without a head is neare corruption and fit onely for the graue, and the common wealth without a Gouernour is as neare vnto ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: on the other ſide, a good Gouernour conſerueth the common wealth in a pious peaceable and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous condition.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In a pious condition:<note place="margin">1 Timoth. 2.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Pray for Kings and for all that are in authority that wee may leade our liues in all godlineſſe</hi> While <hi>Ioſhua</hi> liued, all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſerued the Lord, but he and the godly elders being once buried,<note place="margin">2 Iudges. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.11.</note> they did wickedly in the ſight of the Lord: ſo that a maine cauſe of <hi>Iſraels</hi> godly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment was godly gouernment.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In a peaceable condition:<note place="margin">Acts 24.3.</note> Rulers are ſet ouer a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that they may leade a peaceable life. <hi>Tertullus</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth that by the gouernment of <hi>Foelix</hi> the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince had enioyed great peace, for which hee giueth him great thanks.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In a commodious condition:<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the Ruler is the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God for our good; ſome vnderſtand (good) in that ſenſe as it is vſed in the booke of the Prouerbs:<note place="margin">Proverb. 31.12.</note> a vertuous wife doth her husband good all the dayes of her life, and what good he meaneth is expreſſed in the ſame place; <hi>viz.</hi> ſhe doth preſerue his temporall eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> gained great reſpect, and receiued much honour in his gouernment: whereof a maine cauſe was, becauſe his Subiects liued vnder him both religiouſly, peaceably,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Senec Qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> plus quam alij exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ntſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iudges 21 25.</hi> Pet. Mar. in li. Iudic. Nihil i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> caetu h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>r pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nicioſius, quam ut quiſq, volanta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> ſeq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r.</p>
                  </note> and richly: which point <hi>Seneca</hi> well conſidered, when being asked why the <hi>Spartans</hi> did liue more richly then other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, anſwered: they are better gouerned then other people.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the neceſſity of gouernement, without which no man can liue happily: when there was no ruler in Iſrael, euery man did that which was good in his owne eyes: the meaning whereof <hi>Peter Martir</hi> declareth, viz, they fell from euill to worſe, committing ſinne with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: no wonder if all things were cut of ioynt, where no godly Magiſtrate was either to preſcribe a Law, nor faithfull
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3387:9"/> officers to execute the law preſcribed: whereupon ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſoſt.</note> Take away the Pilot from the ſhip thou ſinkeſt the veſſell; the Captaine from the Army, thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangereſt the whole company; the Ruler from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, thou bereaueſt it of its felicity, animating the godleſſe rout to bite and deuoure one another as Canibals; the greater to conſume the leſſer, the ſtronger to eate vp the weaker, and the rich to oppreſſe the poorer.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">1 Vſe.</note>3 Application vſefull for
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Confutation.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Inſtruction.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Aug. ad Bonifa. Moleſtus eſt medicus furenti phrenetico, &amp; pater indiſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nato ſilio.</note>1 Confutation of that falſe poſition of the Anabaptiſts, viz. Rulers are neither lawfull nor vſefull, either in the Church or in the Common-wealth; who therefore would haue them caſt out as vnſauory ſalt, lopt off as ſuperfluous branches, pulled vp by the rootes as hurtfull weedes, trod vnder foote as ſtinking dung: and that they are men deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing as little honour and reſpect as Sathan who is made mans tormentor. How earneſt and painefull theſe men are in vntwiſting and pulling aſunder the Common wealth from the gouernour whom God hath ioyned together, will plainely appeare by the ſurueigh of thoſe many arguments which they vſe againſt this ordination: as though it were a doctrine againſt nature,<note place="margin">
                     <p n="1">
                        <hi>1 Againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Alſted. Theol. didact. In pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeva illa inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritate poteſtas locum habitura fuiſſet.</p>
                     <p>Cal. inſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>biectio eſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram quanquum miſeria ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis comes non ſit ſecundum natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram.</p>
                     <p>Politicae non minor eſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitas &amp; uſita in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter homines, quam panis, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae, ſolis &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</p>
                  </note> reaſon, and Scripture.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Againſt nature: becauſe Rulers had no exiſtence in the ſtate of innocencie: vnto which allegation, this reply will be ſufficient; that though there was no neede or vſe of rule and dominion before the fall, there being at that time two perſons onely in the world, who as they both were but one family, ſo but one fleſh: yet if that eſtate had longer conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, power and gouernment had neuer the leſſe beene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, though no way troubleſome, as now it is: the which <hi>Caluin</hi> hath moſt learnedly obſerued, who ſaith: Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of one man vnto another, is agreeable vnto nature, though the miſery which ſince the fall accompanieth it, be diſtaſted of nature: and addeth further, that now there is no leſſe vſe or need of gouernment, than of Bread, Water, the Sunne, the Ayre, which as they preſerue men in being
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3387:9"/> and breathing, ſo the other continueth as in a happy kinde of well being. Naturall therefore it is, that the inferiour o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the ſuperiour, the leſſer the greater; without which ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, the ſtate of humane ſociety cannot ſubſiſt: neither indeede is there any thing in the world excellent, which is not ruled and ſupported by gouernment, as we plainely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne in bodies; firſt, <hi>celeſtiall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſt deiure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turali quòd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior ſuo ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ori obediat &amp; minor maiori: ſine quâ rerum humanarum ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus conſervari non poteſt.</note> the Sunne ruling the Moone by night; ſecondly, <hi>terreſtriall</hi> the Beaſts being ſubiect to the Lion, the Birds to the Eagle; thirdly, <hi>artificiall;</hi> in a clocke, the great wheeles guide the leſſe, and the helme, the whole ſhip; fourthly, <hi>politicall,</hi> in military diſcipline, the Generall commandeth the Coronell, he the Captaine, he the Lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, he the Sergeant, he the Corporall, and he the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldier; euery of which faith to his inferiour, goe and he goeth, come and he commeth,<note place="margin">Math. 8.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> doe this and he doth it: all which being well conſidered, how can we conclude any thing againſt this ordinance?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Againſt reaſon,<note place="margin">2 Againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> it being granted (ſay they) that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans being ſanctified perſons, they are a law to themſelues, and neede no other Gouernour, Law nor Ruler, the law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not giuen to a righteous man, but to the diſobedient,<note place="margin">1 Tim 1.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to the vngodly, and ſinners; whereas wee cannot conclude from thence, our exemption from the commandement, but our freedome from puniſhment: we are exempted from the vengeance of the Law, from which vnbeleeuers are not freed, but not from our obedience thereunto. <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Calvin Nulla gens vnquam ſic ab humanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te abhorruit ut non ſe intra le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aliquas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineret. <hi>Iames 3.8.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> no people hath euer as yet beene ſo vnreaſonable, inhumane, and barbarous, as that they will not be confined and bound to ſome lawes: beſides, what little power the man moſt ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified hath to gouerne and regulate himſelfe; wee may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by that which Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh of the tongue: who euer liued ſo to gouerne this little member, as that thereby he hath not often giuen offence both to God, and to his neighbour? <hi>the tongue can no man tame:</hi> from whence I thus inferre, if man hath not power to rule a leſſer mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, then not a greater; if not one, then not many; if not many, then not all; and if not all, then not himſelfe; and doth it ſeeme vnreaſonable that he ſhould haue a Ruler ouer
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3387:10"/> him, who cannot rule himſelfe?</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">3 Againſt the Scriptures.</note>3 Againſt the Scriptures; eſpecially againſt theſe foure pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces.</p>
               <p>The firſt place of Scripture alleadged againſt this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,<note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> is to <hi>Geneſis, Let them rule ouer the fiſh of the ſea, and ouer the fowle of the heauen, and ouer the beaſts:</hi> where GOD g ues <hi>Adam</hi> power ouer all creatures which are vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but not ouer man who is a reaſonable creature: vnto which allegation two things are replyed.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That theſe words were ſpoken vnto <hi>Adam</hi> at that time when as there were no other to gouerne, but vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable creatures; but when as mankind was multiplyed, the law of nature written in their hearts, ere it was written in the tables of ſtone, did dictate vnto their conſciences this truth: <hi>viz.</hi> that euery ſuperiour ſhould be acknowledged and obeyed by his inferiour.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That dominion granted vnto man one way doth not exempt from ſubiection euery way. A bondſlaue hath do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and command ouer all the creatures, yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe is not exempted from his maſters command; the wife hath authority ouer her children and ſeruants which nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth not her husbands authority ouer her. Sathan the god of this world, who ruleth in the hearts of the diſobedient, he guideth them at his pleaſure, yet hereby is he not freed from Gods power, who limiteth and confineth him within his tether: ſo that though the ſuperiours power ouer inferiours is not plainly expreſſed for the reaſons alleaged, yet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thus much is included, that ſubiection is a neceſſary or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</p>
               <p>The ſecond place of Scripture alleaged againſt this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance is in the ſecond Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.11.</note> where <hi>David</hi> calleth vpon Kings and Superiours to kiſſe the Sonne,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Kiſſe the Sonne leſt he be angry;</hi> wherein he chargeth them to lay aſide their power and authority being once conuerted vnto Chriſt: vnto which obiection that learned man M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Calvin</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth well:<note place="margin">Calvin inſtit. lib. p. <hi>727.</hi> N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet imperio d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſito ad priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam vitam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere: ſed pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem qua ſunt inſtructi Chriſto ſubiſcere ut unus inter omnes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mincat.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> though Princes are invited to ador<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt Ieſus, they are not therefore prohibited to exerciſe their magiſteriall power and betake themſelues to a priuate life,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3387:10"/> but they are admoniſhed onely to ſubiect their power to the power Chriſt, and to employ it for the aduancement of his honour: Kings and Princes ought to kiſſe that is to honour Chriſt which is <hi>(ſignum internae reverentie)</hi> a ſigne of inward reuerence, yet are not bound to breake or caſt away the Scepter which is <hi>(Symbolum externae potentiae)</hi> the enſigne of external power granted them fro God.<note place="margin">1 Kings 10.</note> The Queen of <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> though ſhe honoure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> King <hi>Solomon</hi> as the greater light, yet ſhee looſeth not her owne light, but returneth back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with all the honour ſhe brought. That thriſe worthy Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zozom. hiſtor. cecl. lib. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi> Theodoſtus ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecta purpura, relictis imperij inſignibus tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam unus ex plebe coram Deo ſacrificavit.</note> when as he was once conuerted vnto Chriſt, he kiſſed Chriſt the ſonne of God, when putting off his purple robe, and laying aſide his Imperiall Crowne and Scepter, hee went into the Temple, and there bowed downe and worſhipped Chriſt together with the common multitude, which being finiſhed, hee left not his authority or principality, but ſtill held his Empire, and kept his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerainty.</p>
               <p>The third place of Scripture alleaged againſt this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, is in the prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſaiah 49.23.</hi> Calvinus in loc. Non abdicat cos honore, ſed pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronos conſtituit pijs hominibus.</note> where he predicteth that <hi>Kings ſhall be nurſing fathers, and Queenes nurſing mothers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church:</hi> and are thereby called to the exerciſe only of charity, not of authority: the anſwere is, that though they are compared to nurſes, and are bound to foſter the Church, they are not therefore bound to leaue their authority in the Church: a nurſe who hath both a tender heart to affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and alſo full breaſts to ſeede and conſolate her tender babe, doth not throw away her rod which ſerueth both to doctrinate and caſtigate: in a word, as a man hauing wealth is not therefore to abdicate it becauſe he hath got ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with Chriſt, but to honour God with it: ſo a man hauing power muſt not relinquiſh it, but exerciſe it to the honour of God to whom all abſolute and independant power belongeth, and from whom all regall power and ſubordinate authority is deriued.</p>
               <p>The fourth place of Scripture alleaged againſt this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, is in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the Galatians;<note place="margin">Galath 3.28. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> where the Apoſtle ſaith that in Chriſt <hi>there is neither bond nor free,</hi> none
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3387:11"/> ſo bound as to be a ſubiect, none ſo free as to be a Magiſtrate. For the anſwere whereof wee muſt conſider the Church in a double reſpect.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In a ſpirituall reſpect, wherein thou art not reſpected for thy country whether Iewe or Gentile, nor for thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition whether bond or free, nor for thy ſexe whether male or female;<note place="margin">Act. 20.35.</note> 
                  <hi>but in euery Nation he that worketh righteouſneſſe is accepted of God:</hi> if thou beeſt euill the goodneſſe of thy country,<note place="margin">Epiſcop. Sariſb. expoſit in Coloſ. Si Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us ſis at careas renovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, canis es non filius, ſi gentilis ſis eam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> habeas fillus es non am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius canis.</note> pedigree, authority, cannot dignifie thee; and if godly, the baſeneſſe of thy birth, and meanneſſe of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition cannot vilifie thee: ſo ſaith a learned Biſhop in our Church, if thou wert a lewe yet wanteſt ſanctification thou art but a dog, not a childe, and though thou art a Gentile yet haſt holineſſe, thou art not a dog but a ſonne.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In a ciuill reſpect, wherein the diſtinction of bond and free, of ruler and ſubiect is not taken away, but ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſo long as there ſhall bee diſtinction and difference of ſexe and of countryes; as appeareth in the place laſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">2 Vſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</note>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Of inſtruction; wherein we are taught a twofold duty.</head>
               <p n="1">1 Seeing God hath ordeined Rulers, we ought in all our differences to repaire vnto them for ſentence and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,<note place="margin">1 repaire to them. Exod. 18 16. <hi>Venit quiſq, ad me ut Iudicem.</hi> Numb 27.2.</note> which is a maine end of their ordination: thus the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they had any matter of controuerſie they came vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> and he did determine the cauſe, and gaue ſentence: when as the daughters of <hi>Zelophehad</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that they had wrong done vnto them by thoſe who tooke away their fathers lands,<note place="margin">Haereditas inter Hebraeos erat immobilis &amp; perpetua Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel. à Lapid. in loc. <hi>Pſalme 133.</hi>
                  </note> they did repaire vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> for redreſſe, and why did they ſo? becauſe they knew that he was the publique Magiſtrate, ſet vp and ordeined of God for that purpoſe. It were a moſt happy thing for all men to be ſo faſt linked and knit together in vnity and amity as that they might liue without controverſie; but there is great impoſſibility on earth to finde ſuch felicity; becauſe,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Quot homines, tot ſenten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iae.</note>1 All men are not of the ſame iudgement.</p>
               <p n="2">2 All men are not of a peaceable diſpoſition: there is a generation of men ſo froward that like the raging ſea they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3387:11"/> will continually be caſting vp the mire and dirt of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to whom if you ſpeake of peace they will make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ready to battell.</p>
               <p n="3">3 All men are not of a contented minde, in no wiſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with that eſtate which God hath allotted them: who hauing all things ſeruing for neceſſity; yea, wallowing in ſuperfluity, but not therewith content, they couet their neighbours Vineyard, or Aſſe; and hence ariſe ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, according to that old prouerbe,<note place="margin">Haec duo prono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina meum &amp; tuum peperêrunt omne bellum.</note> 
                  <hi>(were it not for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueting, there would be no contending)</hi> and therefore till ſuch time as all different opinions be reconciled, all couetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires ſatisfied, all vnquiet diſpoſitions appeaſed,<note place="margin">Math. 18.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> (which will neuer be ſo long as this world hath a being) there will bee daily differences, and offences will come: for the redreſſe whereof we muſt repaire vnto the Gouernour: <hi>Iethro</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſeth <hi>Moſes</hi> to make choiſe of ſubordinate Rulers,<note place="margin">Exod. 18 22.</note> who might heare the ſmaller matters as well as the weightier: from whence it is euident that all matters of difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt man and man, whether great or ſmall, are to bee brought before the Ruler, and by him to bee determined. The two Harlots being at ods about their Infants,<note place="margin">1 Kings 3.16.</note> they both repaire vnto King <hi>Salomon</hi> for ſentence, whoſe the liuing childe ſhould be, neither of them being a competent iudge in her owne cauſe: the which condemneth the practiſe of thoſe men who will end all differences and controuerſies at the ſharpe:<note place="margin">Aug. in Mat. <hi>26.</hi> Qui nulla legitima pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem alientus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it aut gladio hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano aut gladio vindictae di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinae. <hi>Acts 19.38.</hi>
                  </note> thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did curſed <hi>Cain</hi> end the quarrell betwixt him and his brother, who ought to haue complained vnto his father, (if he had beene iniured) who was then the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, but he contemning his fathers authority, taketh the ſword into his owne hand, and kils his brother. The towne Clarke of <hi>Epheſus</hi> gaue the tumultuous rout of that City good counſell, when they went about to lay violent hands on <hi>Paul: if</hi> Demetrius <hi>or any other man hath any thing to ſay againſt</hi> Paul, <hi>if he hath done any wrong, the bar is open, and there be them that will impleade whatſoeuer can be produced;</hi> Chriſt alloweth not combating cauſeleſſe and perſonall in the field, as appeareth by that his ſpeech to <hi>Peter:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 26.52.</note> 
                  <hi>he that taketh the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword:</hi> hee ſhall fall either by the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3387:12"/> ſword of his aduerſary, or if he eſcape, by the ſword of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is a man bound in euery difference and grieuance to repaire vnto the Gouernour?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We muſt propound ſome caſes ere wee can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the queſtion: for it comes to paſſe,</p>
               <p>Firſt, ſometimes, that the peccant party vpon delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Secundae cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones ſunt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liores.</note> is contented to giue the full ſatisfaction both equiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to thy dammage, and ſutable to thine owne deſire and expectation: in this caſe and for this cauſe <hi>Lot</hi> ſtayed and ended his controuerſie with <hi>Abraham,</hi> he offering vnto <hi>Lot</hi> a fairer end than he either deſired or deſerued.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſometimes, that ſome good neighbour hath ſtept betwixt thee and thy aduerſary as arbitrator, who hath made thee and thy aduerſary friends: ſuch peace-makers be as ſcarce to bee found among vs, as they were among the Corinths,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.5.</note> where there was no man ſo charitable, as to ſtay them in their contentious ſuits, but ſuffered one brother to goe to law with another. One reaſon that there are ſo few vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers in this kinde is, becauſe for the moſt part it is both a burthenſome and thankeleſſe office:<note place="margin">Aug. Mallem per ſingalos dies aliquid manibus operari: quam tumultuoſiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas cauſarum perplexitates pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Math. 5 9.</hi>
                  </note> for which cauſe Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> proteſteth, that hee had rather vndertake the moſt toileſome handy labour, than to be an arbitrator; yet ſuch as are peace-makers, haue great encouragement to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue their godly courſe, becauſe Chriſt hath promiſed a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular bleſſing to ſuch.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſometimes, that thou who haſt ſuffered an iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, art perſwaded by the ſpirit of God freely to forgiue it; and that <hi>Paul</hi> his exhortation hath preuailed with thee, who ſaith thus; <hi>forgiue one another, if any man haue a quarrell to an other,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.13.</note> 
                  <hi>euen as Chriſt forgaue you:</hi> now if the holy Spirit of God doth forcibly moue thee to reconciliation, it will not be good for thee to quench that motion, but to end the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
               <p>Now in theſe caſes as when the cauſe is arbitrated, ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction tendred, and the ſpirit of God hath preuailed, you need not trouble the Gouernour; but in other caſes of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ye may repaire vnto him for aſſiſtance: for the ſame
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3387:12"/> God who giues the commandement to goe to the Miniſter for the preſeruation of thy ſoule, to the Phyſitian for the preſeruation of thy health and life, giueth thee good leaue to goe to the Gouernour for the recouery of thy perſonall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; for to this end and purpoſe hath God ordained magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy and authority.</p>
               <p>The ſecond vſe of inſtruction:<note place="margin">2 Vſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: to honour them. Rom 13.1.7.</note> ſeeing that Gouernours are of Gods ordination, and by him ſet vp aboue others, therefore wee ought to honour them. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth that they ought to be honoured, becauſe they are of GOD ordained: when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had made <hi>Ioſeph</hi> a Gouernour,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.40.43.</note> he cauſed him to be honoured of all the people: ſo Magiſtrates being deputed by God to rule in any part of this his lower houſe vpon earth:<note place="margin">Daniel 3.7.</note> he will haue them to be honoured and highly reſpected. We reade that <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> did ſet vp a liueleſſe Image which hee will haue honoured of all the people, becauſe it was of his deuiſing, and by him erected and ſet vp. God the chiefe Gouernour on earth,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Etſi ſunt homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ante deum, at dij ante homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
                     <p>Muſc. in Pſal. <hi>82.</hi> Dij propter imperandi iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. <hi>1 Obiection. 1 Pet. 2.17.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> he ſetteth vp the Magiſtrate, who is his liuely image reſembling him in power, (and therefore called Gods) though not (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) by reaſon of their nature, yet (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) by reaſon of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and employment; and he will ſeuerely torture in the fiery furnace of hell, all ſuch as will not yeeld honour to theſe liuing images which he hath ſet vp, either in ſuperiour or inferiour place.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Obiect.</hi> Honour is not a priuiledge onely belonging vnto the Gouernour, for as much as he that ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> honour the King, ſaith alſo in the ſame verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> honour all men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solut.</hi> We ought both to honour the King,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Solut.</hi> Gorran. in loc. Omnes. debemus honorare interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us: at regem &amp; magiſtratum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius. <hi>Rom. 12.10. 2. Obiection.</hi>
                  </note> who is the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, as alſo euery equall and inferiour; but with great difference: we muſt honour all godly men with the honour of curteſie, as the Apoſtle commandeth, <hi>(in giuing honour, goe one before another)</hi> but wee muſt honour the King with the honour of loyalty.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Obiection:</hi> the Gouernour being of a meaner pedigree and deſcent, am I bound to honour him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi> It is an ordinary thing with GOD to promote<note place="margin">Sol.</note>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:3387:13"/> men of meane degree vnto the office of Magiſtracy:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>he lifteth vp the beggar from the dunghill, and ſetteth him with Princes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hannah:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal. 75.6.</hi> He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t cuſtos pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cudum, hodie hominum.</note> thus God dealt with <hi>Dauid, hee tooke him from following of the Ewes with lambe, and ſet him with the Princes of his people:</hi> therefore we muſt not murmure or repine at the worke of the Lord promoting men of meane ranke aboue vs,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.28.</note> as did <hi>Dauids</hi> brethren when they ſaw him in the campe, and the Iewes who would not honour Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> becauſe hee was but a Carpenters ſonne; but let vs be alwaies willing and ready to giue all reſpect and reuerence to ſuch as God hath honoured with authority; all which muſt be giuen euen to the meaneſt whomſoeuer the King of heauen will honour.</p>
               <p>Therefore let us reſolue to honour them <hi>corde, ore, opere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Corde.</hi> Eccl. 10.20.</note>1 <hi>Corde, in heart: curſe not the King, no not in thy thought, for a bird of the ayre ſhall carry the voyce, and that which hath wings ſhall vtter the matter:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Lor. Act. <hi>26 25.</hi> Non propter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptam iniuriam voluit denegare honoris ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium titulum. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>2</hi> Ore.</note>2 <hi>Ore,</hi> in words, and that three wayes:</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Tribuendo illis titulos reuerentiae:</hi> by giuing them titles of honour and reuerence, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth vnto <hi>Feſtus</hi> when he pleaded before him for his life, the title he gaue him was (moſt noble <hi>Feſtus</hi>) vpon which words <hi>Lorinus</hi> ſaith thus; though <hi>Feſtus</hi> had iniured him in words, calling him a mad and franticke fellow; yet he giueth vnto <hi>Feſtus</hi> that ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and honourable title which did belong vnto him.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6.9.</hi> Aegardus. Nihil aegetus ſeras quam numen magiſtratus rodi &amp; deformart.</note>2 <hi>Defendendo contra detractores &amp; obtrectatores,</hi> by defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them againſt all detractors and calumniators: <hi>Abiſha</hi> would not with any patience endure the rayling calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Shemei</hi> againſt his Soueraigne: we may not conniue at others who doe it; much leſſe may we take liberty to doe it our ſelues,<note place="margin">Exod. 22.28.</note> it being flatly prohibited by <hi>Moſes: thou ſhalt not rayle vpon the Iudge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>1 Tim. 2.1.</hi> Cal. in loc. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi videtur Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus conſul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ò tres voces in eundem ſinem ſimul con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re; ut pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi ſtudium &amp; aſſiduitatem magis commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det ac vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiùs urgeat. <hi>3</hi> Opere.</p>
                     <p>Evangelium non tollit praecepta nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rae ſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iohn 1.29.</hi> Non venu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus ut toll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ret tura, ſed peccata mandi. Chryſoſt. <hi>3 Orect. Sol.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>neither ſpeake euill of the Ruler of thy people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Orando,</hi> by praying earneſtly vnto God for a bleſſing vpon them as we are enioyned by Saint <hi>Paul: I exhort that ſupplications, prayers, and interceſſions, be made for Kings, and all that are in authoritie.</hi> Maſter <hi>Caluin</hi> giueth a reaſon why the Apoſtle vſeth all theſe three words; Supplications, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, interceſſions, <hi>viz.</hi> that he might the better commend
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3387:13"/> vnto vs the aſſiduity of prayer for ſuch as are in authority.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Opere</hi> in obeying their lawes, mandates, and iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for though we liue in the time of the Goſpell, yet the Goſpell doth not ouerthrow or nulliſie natures law or Gods law, but doth rather ratifie and confirme them: Chriſt the Lambe of God (ſaith one) came not into the world to take away and aboliſh the wholeſome lawes and conſtitutions, but the ſinne and tranſgreſſions thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Obiection:</hi> The Ruler being a wicked man, am I bound to honour and obey him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Replicat.</hi> God oftentimes hath ſuffered wicked men to haue authority and power, as is euident in the Booke of the <hi>Chronicles</hi> of the Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and that for two reaſons:</p>
               <p n="1">1 For the probation of his ſeruants integrity;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou. 28.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Anſelm. Si bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus nutritor tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ſi malus ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator tuus.</note> 
                  <hi>when the wicked come vp, the man is tryed:</hi> wicked Gouernours are like vnto ſo many hot furnaces wherein the godly are tryed: <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was <hi>Daniels</hi> furnace, <hi>Herod</hi> was <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Nero</hi> was Saint <hi>Pauls,</hi> wherein and whereby they were throughly tried, and out whence they came purer then the fineſt gold.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For their owne ſpeedy deſtruction: wicked Rulers are like ſhips full fraught with iniquity, wherein Authority is the top ſaile, which being violently driuen with the breath of the diuels mouth, hurrieth them ſpeedily into the dead ſea of deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Now ſuppoſe that a wicked man is ſet ouer thee, then which euill in this life, none can bee greater, vnleſſe that which withall <hi>Dauid</hi> wiſhed to gods enemy:<note place="margin">Pſal. 109.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Set thou the wicked ouer him, and let Sathan ſtand at his right hand;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> yet to ſuch a one thou muſt be ſubiect, ſuch a one thou muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, not denying thine obedience in thoſe things wherein thou art not compelled to breake the law of God; for if thou beeſt commanded to doe things expreſly vnlawfull, thou muſt call to mind the ſpeech of that godly martyr to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour; I dare not fulfill thy pleaſure;<note place="margin">Da v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am ó impe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ator, tu carcorem, ille ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>naam mina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> I doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence thee who haſt power to impriſon and kill my body, but I doe much more feare to diſobey his command who hath power to caſt both my body and ſoule into the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3387:14"/> paines of hell fire:<note place="margin">Aug. Bonis in malo ſcienter non obedias, nec malis in bono contradicas.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> giueth a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent rule in this caſe, who ſaith, As we muſt not obey godly Rulers in their vniuſt commands, ſo muſt we not diſobey wicked Rulers in their iuſt iniunctions.</p>
               <p>And for the concluſion of this firſt part of the text, let this be remembred; euer to baniſh from our hearts and thoughts that papall and poyſonfull doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> which tolerateth, yea animateth ſubiects to take armes againſt their ſoueraigne Princes, commanding only ſomething to them vnpleaſing; though neuer ſo lawfull in it ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2 Kings 11.16.</hi> Regula. A facto extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinario non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet inferri gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis concluſio de re extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria. Scharpius.</note> and well pleaſing vnto God; ſtrongly enforcing the doctrine of rebellion from ſome particular inſtances in the Scriptures as <hi>Athaliah</hi> and the like examples, wreſting ſuch places to their owne ends and purpoſes, which being right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtood, doe no way iuſtify their practiſes: this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was neither belieued nor practiſed by the holy mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, no not in the ſcorching hotteſt times of perſecution: in the time when <hi>Tertullian</hi> liued, there was a hot fire kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and prepared by bloudy minded Princes, for the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of poore Chriſtians: at which time he thus aduiſeth them: we might reuenge our ſelues to the full vpon our perſecuting Gouernors, hauing euery day ſufficient aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt them;<note place="margin">Tertull. Abſit ut igne humano vindicetur ſecta divina.</note> but farre be it from vs, that wee ſhould blemiſh our moſt glorious profeſſion with cruell trucidati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: we muſt chuſe rather to ſuffer an vndeſerued death as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours, then to put to death our ſuperiours: prayers and teares theſe are weapons well beſeeming the lambes and doues of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Apud noſtram diſciplinam mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri licet magis quam occîdere. Ibidem.</note> Let vs carry in the one hand the buckler of innocencie, and in the other the ſhield of patience; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe to beare off a blow, then a ſword to giue a blow, recompenſing no man euill for euill, but committing thy cauſe vnto him who will iudge righteouſly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſo much of the firſt generall part</hi> viz. <hi>Subiect:</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3387:14"/>
            <head>The ſecond Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THe ſecond generall is the Predicate,</hi> Faithfull; <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in foure things are to be handled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Expoſition,</hi> 2 <hi>Illuſtration,</hi> 3 <hi>Obſervation,</hi> 4 <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Expoſition,</hi> wherein two things are vnfolded.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In what ſenſe he was faithfull;</p>
            <p>Such are called faithfull in Scripture, as are</p>
            <p n="1">1 Stedfaſt beleeuers of Gods Word and promiſes;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> many of which ſort there were, ſome in Epheſus, when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle writ his Epiſtle vnto them, which he directed to the faithfull in Chriſt there: to this kinde of faithfulneſſe our Sauiour exhorteth <hi>Thomas,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Iohn 20.27. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 Cor. 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>bee not faithleſſe, but faithfull:</hi> this is that faithfulneſſe which is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to infidelity, as appeareth by Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpeech; <hi>what part hath the Beleeuer with the Infidell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Sincere profeſſors of godlineſſe, ſuch as worſhip God in ſincerity; for ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> a man King <hi>Salomon</hi> ſought, but could ſcarce finde him,<note place="margin">Prouerb. 20.6.</note> 
               <hi>many men will boaſt of their owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but who can finde a faithfull man?</hi> Many there are who haue a good out-ſide, with the Phariſee, but few that haue <hi>Nathaniels</hi> inward ſinceritie: this is faithfulneſſe oppoſed to hypocriſie.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Conſcionable diſchargers of that office and place wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God hath betruſted them:<note place="margin">Math. 25.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> he in the parable to whom the Maſter of the family gaue fiue talents, with which he gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned other fiue, is approued and commended for faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in theſe words; <hi>well done thou good and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant:</hi> where he is called faithfull, becauſe he did conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly diſcharge the charge hee vndertooke: on the contrary, God complaineth, becauſe Iſrael wanted this faithfulneſſe; <hi>Iſrael was not faithfull in his couenant:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.37.</note> the people made many couenants with the Lord, and many promiſes to him, but no conſcience to pay what they had vowed, or to diſcharge what they had couenanted; this is the faithfulneſſe oppoſed to <hi>foedifragie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3387:15"/>
            <p>In all which reſpects, <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithfull, he was a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full beleeuer of Gods word and promiſes,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.14.</note> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth teſtifie; he was ſincere without hypocriſie, as the Greeke particle (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) doth intimate;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> verily he was faithfull (that is) in verity: and alſo he was faithfull in the diſcharge of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, as is euident throughout the hiſtory.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to be vnfolded is, in whoſe houſe hee was faithfull; in his houſe: the word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) hath reference to the laſt word of the former verſe, which is God; ſo that the ſenſe is this: he was faithfull in Gods houſe.</p>
            <p>God hath three houſes wherein it pleaſeth him to reſide,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 3.20. Heb. 3 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Io. 14 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Tim. 3.15. 2 Tim. 2.20. <hi>Aretius in locum Haec domus erat populus Iudao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
               </note>1 An inner houſe, which is <hi>(iuſti virianima)</hi> the heart and ſoule of the godly man: <hi>he that heareth my voyce, I will come in vnto him. Whoſe houſe yeare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 An vpper houſe which is <hi>(coeleſtis patria)</hi> the kingdome of heauen which is called <hi>our fathers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 An outer houſe which is <hi>(militans eccleſia)</hi> and called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a great houſe; and in this houſe was <hi>Moſes</hi> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as <hi>Aretius</hi> noteth. This houſe was the people of the Iewes, whoſe Gouernour was <hi>Moſes,</hi> the which houſe though it was very great in the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet ſince the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt it is much inlarged.</p>
            <p>This people of Iſrael in the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> did much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble a houſhold.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Propter obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiam.</note>1 <hi>Propter populi obedientiam oeconomo &amp; miniſtro;</hi> in euery houſhold there is a Maſter or Gouernour, to whom all in the family doe yeeld obedience; which is according vnto <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi> his proclamation,<note place="margin">Heſter 1.22.</note> who did enact and proclaime this law; that euery man ſhould beare rule in his own houſe; ſo this houſhold of Iſrael, they were both obedient to God the owner of the houſe, and to <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſteward of the houſe,<note place="margin">Ioſhua. 1.17.</note> as is plainely euident by their ſpeech vnto <hi>Ioſhua; as we obeyed Moſes in all things, ſo will wee thee, if God bee with thee, as he was with</hi> Moſes.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Propter pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatem.</note>2 <hi>Propter paucitatem:</hi> the gouernment of a family is the leaſt regiment: the gouernment of Empires &amp; Kingdomes that is the higheſt, next thereunto of Prouinces, then of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, then of Townes, then of Villages, and laſt of all, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3387:15"/> is leaſt of all, of Houſholds. The people of Iſrael compared with the Egyptians and other their enemies,<note place="margin">Numerus minor, at melior.</note> were but as a houſhold; that is, but as a handfull, a very fewe, a ſmall number.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Propter familiae vnitatem:</hi> families are,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3</hi> Propter uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem.</note> or ought to bee vnited, not diuided: our Sauiour ſaith, that a houſe diuided againſt it ſelfe, cannot ſtand. All the while that <hi>Moſes</hi> gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Iſrael, they were cloſely combined together, except ſome few irregular perſons, whoſe diuiſion <hi>Moſes</hi> laboureth to reforme; <hi>why ſmiteſt thou thy fellow?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 2 13.</note> though afterwards ſome tribes falling off, they were ruinated and ſcattered.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee how he was faithfull, &amp; in whoſe houſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond generall in the Praedicate is the <hi>Illuſtration.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Illuſtration.</note>
               </head>
               <p>Wherein you may take a full view of <hi>Moſes</hi> his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe:</p>
               <p>His faithfulneſſe is illuſtrated partly by
<list>
                     <item>1 His Adaptation to his office.</item>
                     <item>2 His Execution of that office.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Adaptatione,</hi> by his fitneſſe for the office:<note place="margin">1 Adaptation.</note> hee was fitted for the faithfull execution of his office two wayes:
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Scientia,</hi> by his knowledge.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Conſcientia,</hi> by his conſcience.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Science,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Scientia.</note> it is an vndoubted truth that that man cannot be faithfull in his office, who therein is not skilfull. <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſo skilfull both in humane and diuine knowledge as that he was admired by the moſt learned of his time,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Scientia hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Act. 7.22.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Mercatura bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum artium. Iuſtinus quaeſt. <hi>25.</hi> ad Orthodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xos.</p>
                     <p>Barrad. Itinerar. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum oculi lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem indigent ut videant, ſic prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes &amp; duces apientiae ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore opus habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, ut rempub. recte ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrent.</p>
                     <p>Diodorus Siculus Vt urbanitatem, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>gantiam, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitatem, al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, quaſi rector populi ſuturus, add ſecret, &amp; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> haberet. Scientia divino.</p>
                  </note> and ſuch as haue liued ſince.</p>
               <p n="1">1 For humane knowledge he was eminent, as S. <hi>Steuen</hi> auoucheth, he was learned in all the learning of the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians; where was kept the common mart of all learned Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> ſaith that there he was taught the art of Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Arithmetick, Muſicke and Aſtronomy together with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grounds of Polity. It hath beene alwayes held conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, Gouernours ſhould haue ſome knowledge of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne and nationall lawes; they are the eyes of the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon wealth, as the eyes ſtand in neede of light that they may ſee and diſcerne; ſo Rulers of wiſdome in humane
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3387:16"/> things, that they may rightly gouerne. Wherefore (ſaith <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi>) God would haue <hi>Moſes</hi> to be brought vp in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court; euen for this cauſe, that hee might there learne ciuility, elegancy, magnanimity, liberality; together with all other vertues which might beſeeme a Gouernour.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For diuine knowledge, he was excellent as appeareth by thoſe large volumes, of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> which declareth the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the world, and the gouerning of it for the ſpace of one thouſand three hundred ſixty and eight yeares, of <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> wherein is declared the departure of Iſrael out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, and what was done from the death of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> vntill the yeare wherin God commanded the Tabernacle to be built: of <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> wherein is deſcribed the office of the Leuiticall P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieſthood, and thoſe many ceremonies, all which did aime at Chriſt: of <hi>Numbers,</hi> wherein is ſet downe the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Iſraelites in the deſart, vntill the time that they tooke poſſeſſion of Canaan, with their demeanour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition for thirtie eight yeares together: and of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> wherein <hi>Moſes</hi> did repeate the Law to the Iſraelites, and ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Gods benefits in their audience, to draw them vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: all which being conſidered, we cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe conclude then that <hi>Moſes</hi> was very skilfull in the Law of God.</p>
               <p>We reade of none either renowned for, or faithfull in gouernment, but ſuch as haue been prudent and intelligent, well doctrinated both in humane and diuine knowledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſeph.</hi> Gen. 41.48.</note>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> whom <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſet,</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Super horrea totius Aegypti,</hi> and made him Puru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iour f r his Corne, and Warden of his Granaries.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 41.40.</note>2 <hi>Super domum &amp; aulam eius;</hi> and made him the Lord Controller of his Court; <hi>thou ſhalt be ouer mine houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 41.40.</note>3 <hi>Super milites;</hi> hee was the Lord Lieuetenant ouer his Armies in the time of warre; <hi>at thy word ſhall all my people be armed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 41.41.</note>4 <hi>Super totum populum,</hi> he was Lord Preſident ouer all his ſubiects.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 41.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</note>And the Hiſtory telleth vs why he had all theſe honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble offices conferred vpon him; <hi>becauſe there was no man like
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3387:16"/> vnto him for wiſedome and vnderſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> was made a Ruler in Iſrael,<note place="margin">Dauid.</note> becauſe of his excellent wiſedome, both in matters (litigious) which <hi>Ioab</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.20.</note> 
                  <hi>my Lord is wiſe according to the wiſedome of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of God, to vnderſtand all things that are in the earth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 119.99.100.</note> and in matters religious, wherein he was wiſer then his Aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, then his Teachers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salomon,</hi> becauſe he was ſo greatly learned,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Salomon.</hi> 1 Kings 3.28.</note> therefore was his gouernment ſo much admired, both of his owne Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, who ſaw the wiſedome of God in him to <hi>doe iuſtice,</hi> as alſo among ſtrangers renowned:<note place="margin">1 Kings 4.34.</note> 
                  <hi>All people came from all parts of the earth to heare his wiſedome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> requireth wiſedome in all thoſe whom hee ſhall approue of for gouernment,<note place="margin">Duet. 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>bring men of wiſedome and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and I will make them Rulers ouer you,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> though but a heathen man,<note place="margin">Dan. 1.4.</note> yet would haue ſuch as he intended to promote to any office or digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be brought vp in learning and vnderſtanding, and able to vtter knowledge; who when himſelfe was depriued of vnderſtanding, (as a man vnworthy to gouerne) did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh the ſocietie of men, and liued among beaſts.</p>
               <p>So that it is very needfull for a Gouernour to get the knowledge of humane lawes;<note place="margin">
                     <p>Baſil. Hom. <hi>12.</hi> Iuſtitiam cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcere, facit, ut rem recte iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re poſſimus: im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibile namque eſt, non verſatum et inexercitatum in iuſti cognitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, rem dubiam, &amp; in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia poſitam, bene ac ordine diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere.</p>
                     <p>Aurelius Victor Domi ſanctita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: foris forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem: utro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> prudentiam. <hi>Deut. 17.19.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> whereof Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpeaketh thus; <hi>by knowing what iuſtice is rightly, a man is enabled to iudge exactly;</hi> and verily it ſeemeth a thing impoſſible, that hee who hath no knowledge of the law, ſhould rightly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine according to the law: for the which cauſe <hi>Aurelius <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor</hi> was wont to ſay, three things there are which the people may expect in and from their Gouernour: firſt, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie in the time of peace: ſecondly, fortitude in the time of war: thirdly, ſapiency and wiſedome in them both. But chiefly and aboue all, his care muſt be to acquaint himſelfe throughly with the law of God. This is that law which muſt often be ſounded in the eares of ſuch, laid before the eyes of ſuch; <hi>he that is thy King and gouernour, the law ſhall be with him, and he ſhall reade therein all the dayes of his life;</hi> and fluent in the mouthes of ſuch, as <hi>Dauid, I will ſpeake of thy commandements, euen before Kings:</hi> theſe are thoſe lawes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3387:17"/> whereupon his heart did muſe and meditate,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal 45.1.</hi> Affirmo multo chariores mihi eſſe ſacras ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turas quam reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num; &amp; ſi alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utro m hi ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum fit aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimius n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demati, quam ſcripturis cariu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Conſcientiâ.</note> and on which his tongue did talke; valuing them as highly as that Sicili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King, who ſaid, he had rather loſe all his regall honour, then the company of the Scripture; as knowing that hee ſhould be vnfit for gouernment, vnleſſe he had direction from thence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2 Conſcientia;</hi> hee was fitted vnto faithfulneſſe by the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of his conſcience.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> had not beene fit for gouernement, had not his conſcien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e beene as good as his ſcience. Little comfort or b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fit ſhall men rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e from their Gouernours, though ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly skilfull, and able, vnleſſe they be conſcionable. That gouernment is very irkeſome and peccant, where the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers conſcience is exorbitant; <hi>viz</hi> when it is either too</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1. laſt.</note>1 Spatious, taking liberty to doe all things vnlawfull himſelfe, with <hi>Ahab,</hi> who ſold himſelfe to doe wickedly, and to commit iniquity with greedneſſe and delight; or giuing like liberty to others</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. de Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſib. Manichaei ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> voluerunt he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bas evellere, nec poma dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere.</note>2 Scrupulous denying themſelues that liberty which God hath giuen them; as the Maniches, who would not kill cattell to eate, leaſt they ſhould breake the ſixt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, no, not ſo much they durſt as to plucke an herbe or pull an apple from the tree, leſt they ſhould deſtroy the life of theſe vegetables.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23.24.</note>3 Prepoſterous, as the Phariſees, who did ſtarine at Gnats, but ſwallow Camels;<note place="margin">
                     <p>Philo. Iudaeus Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ales trat ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is erat vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, cum wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> diſcreparet haud a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iter quam in inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mento mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſico.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>2 Sam. 15.4.</hi> Pandulphus <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Math. 13.3.</hi> Philo Mentem factis exprimens facta dictis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodans. Executione.</p>
                  </note> puniſhing leſſer offences moſt ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and letting greater paſſe careleſly.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Moſes</hi> hee had a good conſcience, as <hi>Philo</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: ſuch as his language was, ſo was his life, harmonizing ſweetly together as in a muſicall inſtrument; far vnlike vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abſolon,</hi> who was ſufficiently witty and eloquent, which his ſpeech vnto the people doth witneſſe: <hi>let thy matter bee good, and come vnto mee, and I will doe thee iuſtice;</hi> yet had no co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcience, like to <hi>Pandulphus</hi> his ſchollars, who had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſpeake well, yet neuer would doe well; and to the Phariſees, who ſaid, but did not: but <hi>Moſes</hi> his heart and tongue did moue together: what his appearance was, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3387:17"/> he was in ſubſtance: <hi>expreſſing his minde by his actions, and applying his actions according to his communications.</hi> And thus much of his Adaptation to faithfulneſſe in his office.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Executione,</hi> he was faithfull in the execution of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and this will appeare in three ſeuerall obiects.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithfull
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Deo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Sacerdoti.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Populo.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Deo,</hi> to God who ordained him a Gouernour,<note place="margin">Deo.</note> and this faithfulneſſe he teſtified to God three wayes.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Fide,</hi> by his faith in God.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Pietate,</hi> by his pietie towards God.</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Zelo,</hi> by his zeale for God.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Fide,</hi> by his faith in God, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Fide.</hi> Heb. 11 23.24.27. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> that he was a true beleeuer: <hi>by ſaith he refuſed to be called the ſonne of</hi> Pharaohs <hi>daughter, by faith he forſooke Egypt, by ſaith he ordained the Paſſeouer, and paſſed through the red Sea, as on drie land;</hi> concluding againſt all carnall reaſon and ſence, that the Egyptians whom now they beheld, ſhould neuer any more be ſeene of them: hee beleeued whatſoeuer God had predicted, notwithſtanding that it ſeemed impoſſible to be effected.<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>2</hi> Pietate. <hi>Exod. 3.5.</hi> Theodoret. in queſtionibus in Exod. Vt religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſiorem hac rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Moſen red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret.</p>
                     <p>Gregor <hi>2</hi>a. part. paſtorum Moſes crebro taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum intrat, &amp; exit: exemplum praebens rectori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ut cum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ambigunt, dominum per o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant. <hi>Iam 5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>6. Exod 17.11.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Pietate,</hi> by his piety towards God, when God called him to the office of Magiſtracy, he commanded him <hi>to put off his ſhooes,</hi> thereby admoniſhing him (as <hi>Theodoret</hi> noteth) to put off all carnall and ſinfull affections, and to become ſtedfaſtly religious. Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Moſes</hi> did goe very frequently into the Tabernacle, therein giuing a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly example vnto Gouernours, that when they doubt what is to be done, they ſhould in a deuout manner aske counſell of God. No queſtion but <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſuch a one himſelfe, as he made choiſe of for Gouernours: that is, one fearing God. Had not <hi>Moſes</hi> beene a man of extraordinary piety, he could not haue beene of that preualency with God, as to turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his wrath: it being not the prayer of euery man, but onely of the godly man which preuaileth much: exceeding much did <hi>Moſes</hi> preuaile with God in the behalfe of Iſrael, whoſe hands (when he prayed) were ſtrengthened againſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3387:18"/> their enemies: the which care of godlineſſe we may ſee both in <hi>Ioſhua,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſhua 24.15.</note> who was <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſucceſſor, whoſe reſolution was, that he and his houſe would ſerue the Lord; and in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> who being as great a Builder, as his father was a Warriour; he erecting a dwelling houſe for his own ſafetie; building a throne to iudge cauſes, for the vpholding of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;<note place="margin">1 Kings 6.14.</note> ſo alſo hee built a ſtately Temple vnto God for the ſupportance of Gods worſhip and piety: remembring well the counſell of his deceaſed father, <hi>thou ſhalt beare rule in the feare of the Lord:</hi> the which aduiſe all Gouernours muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>2 Sam. 23.3. 3 Zeale. Deut. 9.17.</hi> Ambr. <hi>56.</hi> epiſt. Fractae ſunt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a ut repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur ſecundae. Jſidor Hae tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae imaginem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſirabant pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcae legis, quae fracta eſt &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gata.</p>
                     <p>Manet &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebit Decalogus, manebunt libri <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eteris teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, quia ſpiritus ſanctus non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>teri quam in novo. Hic. on. ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulum. Moyſes zelo dei permo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, tabulas f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git in deteſtatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem idololatriae. <hi>Deut. 34 6.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sozomen. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi> Qudam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nt in Arabia qui adorant Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> imaginem. Ambr. Opinor Moſen non eſſe mortuum, ſed tantum dici mortuum &amp; tranſlatum eſſe tantum inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r Eliae. <hi>Deut. 34.6.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> together with the ſaying of <hi>Conſtantine, viz.</hi> hee that is vngodly and vnfaithfull towards God, will neuer be faithfull vnto men.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Zelo,</hi> by his zeale for God: we reade in the Scripture that he brake the Tables of ſtone; why he did ſo, there are ſundry reaſons giuen by ſeuerall Writers.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, that by this action, was ſhadowed out the aboliſhing of the olde Law, and the eſtabliſhing of the Goſpell: and of the ſame iudgement is <hi>Iſidore, theſe Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles did repreſent the olde law which is abrogated and broken:</hi> wheras the Decalogue together with other books of the old Teſtament, ſhall abide and remaine in the world to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry end of the world, as well as the new; becauſe the Spirit of God is the ſpeaker in the olde, as well as in the new.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, that the cauſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> his action, was his zealous affection, becauſe they had prouoked God by their idolatry; in deteſtation whereof he brake the Tables; and the hiſtory relateth vnto vs other paſſages of <hi>Moſes</hi> his zeale: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e knowing that the Iewes did extraordinarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect him, therefore hee would not let the place of his buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all be knowne; his zealous heart fearing leſt after his death, the ſuperſtitious Iewes ſhould worſhip his dead body: <hi>no man knoweth of his Sepulcher vnto this day.</hi> It is reported, that in <hi>Arabia</hi> at this day ſome doe worſhip and adore the image of <hi>Moſes.</hi> O how many moe Idolaters would there be, had they the true body of <hi>Moſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee muſt not hold in opinion with <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who thought that <hi>Moſes</hi> dyed not, but is onely ſaid ſo to be:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3387:18"/> whereas God decreeth that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall dye in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that <hi>Aaron</hi> did; and in the booke of <hi>Deuteronomie,</hi> the land where he was buried is mentioned, namely the land of <hi>Moab,</hi> and that in ſome valley in that land, but whether in the valley of <hi>Phogor,</hi> as ſome affirme, or in what other, it is vnknowne: but he earneſtly deſired of God, as ſome thinke, that it might not be knowne,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Chryſoſt. Hom <hi>1.</hi> in Matthaeum. Ne Hebraei cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus cius utpote ducis &amp; legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris, velut nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quiddam colerent.</p>
                     <p>Auguſt. de mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab. ſcript. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>35.</hi> Virg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m qua ſigna multa fecerat, ne ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raretur, ſecum abſtulerat. Sacerdoti.</p>
                  </note> leſt (as Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) idolaters might adore his body being dead, whom they ſo highly honoured being liuing. O behold now his exceeding zeale for Gods glory, who would rather bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of an honourable interm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, then that thereby Gods honour ſhould receiue any detriment: and as much wee might ſpeake of his like zeale in hiding of his rod, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> giues, <hi>viz.</hi> leſt God thereby might be diſhonoured.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2 <hi>Sacerdoti.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="2">2 He was faithfull to <hi>Aaron</hi> his elder brother, who was Gods Prieſt, as will appeare in theſe three particulars,
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Deprecando.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Dirigendo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Amplexando.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Deprecando,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deprecando.</note> intreating and begging pardon for <hi>Aarons</hi> foule fact: the text ſaith that the Lord was very <hi>angry with Aaron, euen to deſtroy him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and at that time Moſes prayeth for Aaron;</hi> not vnlike vnto <hi>Ionathan,</hi> who when as <hi>Saul</hi> was angry with <hi>Dauid,</hi> hee intercedeth for him vnto the King,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.7.</note> and getteth him into fauour againe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Dirigendo,</hi> directing what hee ought to doe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dirigendo.</hi> Exod. 4.15.16.</note> this was Gods command vnto <hi>Moſes, that he ſhould ſpeake vnto Aaron, and put words in his mouth, and then he ſhould be as his mouth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Bucholcerus I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſag Eius balbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus erat natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſal. 103 7.</hi> Notas fecit via<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſuas Moſi. Phila. Moſes ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t quae agend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſunt, tanquam intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus concipiens: Aaron ca lem le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur, tanquam o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>exequtus.</p>
                     <p>Amplexando. Aldedius. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratus conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt externa obedientia, at miniſterium ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatur circa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientias.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Philo</hi> ſaith that <hi>Moſes</hi> did ſtammer in his ſpeech, and that <hi>Aaron</hi> was eloquent; wherefore <hi>Aaron</hi> muſt be the ſpeaker but <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt be his director, inſtructing him both what he ſhall ſpeake, and what he ſhall doe. God mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his wayes knowne vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> made them knowne vnto <hi>Aaron:</hi> which kinde of gouernement much differeth from that which now is, wherein though the Magiſtrate gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3387:19"/> the Miniſter by the power of the ſword, yet the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter directeth the Gouernour by the light of Gods word.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Amplexando,</hi> familiarly embracing him as his aſſiſtant in gouernment. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> did differ in ſome things, as doe all other Magiſtrates and Miniſters: as namely,</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Obiectis,</hi> in the obiect of their gouernment; the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate his care is the regularizing of the outward man; the Miniſters ſpeciall care is the conformity of the inward man. When I ſay the obiect of the Magiſtrate is the outward man, I would not be miſtaken, as if it were enough to render to the Magiſtrate a formall and internall obedience, (my meaning is) that the Magiſtrate cannot diſcerne the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of the heart, and by conſequence, not puniſh them.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Vnus per gladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um corpora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em, alter per legis &amp; diſciplinae ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. <hi>Numb. 3 38.</hi> Cornel. à Lapid. Simul hic degere iubentur Moſes &amp; Aaron ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fex.</note>2 <hi>Poena,</hi> the Magiſtrate puniſheth offenders by corporall caſtigation; the Miniſter puniſheth delinquents by eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall excommunication.</p>
               <p>Now though theſe two perſons were thus differenced in their ſeuerall offices of Magiſtracy and Miniſtry; yet ſtraitly were they combined together in louing affection. <hi>Moſes</hi> giuing vnto <hi>Aaron</hi> the right hand of fellowſhip. When the Tabernacle was built (many are of opinion) that as at the Weſt ſide thereof the Gerſhonites pitched their Tents, and there inhabited;<note place="margin">
                     <p>Rupertus. Quia regum gladijs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſacerdotalis poteſtas, &amp; ſicut nihil tutiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s cum ſibi conveniunt, ſic mihi perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſius cum diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiunt. <hi>Exod. 4.14. Exod. 4.27.</hi> Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Incognitus in Pſal.</p>
                     <p>Diverſae erant illorum functio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, utraeque ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarae populo. Muſc.</p>
                  </note> and as at the North ſide the Merarites, at the South the <hi>Kohathites:</hi> ſo at the Eaſt, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched both their Tents. <hi>Rupertus</hi> giues the reaſon why theſe two were appointed to dwell ſo neare together, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew that the publike miniſtry ſtands in need of Magiſteriall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, both whom when agreeing together, nothing is more auſpicious; ſo when they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar and differ, nothing is more dangerous. A happy meeting of theſe two men it was, if <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſo glad of <hi>Aarons</hi> company, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was of <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſociety and familiarity: who when he met <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Horeb,</hi> he kiſſed him, and was glad thereof in his heart, as the Lord told <hi>Moſes.</hi> The ſpeech of <hi>Salomon</hi> is moſt true in gouernment, that theſe two together, are better than to be ſeuered aſunder: their offices indeed were diuers, but their affections alike; neither of them diſdaine the other,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3387:19"/> but each of them did ſupport the other;<note place="margin">Muſculus in <hi>77.</hi> Pſal. Ambo ſervi manebant, neuter domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um uſurpabat.</note> for which combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and bleſſed vnion of Magiſtrate and Miniſter, we are daily to beg of God who is the God of peace and order.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>3 <hi>Populo.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Hee was faithfull to the people of God as appeareth by theſe three things:<note place="margin">3 <hi>Populo.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Diligentia,</hi> by his diligence for them.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Dilectione,</hi> by his loue towards them.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Iuſtitia,</hi> by his doing of iuſtice among them.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 His diligence for them in hearing and determining of their cauſes: he ſlept vp to the beach in the morning,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Diligenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Exod. 18.14.</note> and came not downe till the euening,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod. 18.18.</hi> Extra vires tuas eſt negotium. <hi>Rom. 12.14.</hi> Picrius Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyp. l <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> Tam magnos ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet oculos, &amp; palpelras adeo parvas, ut non poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t oculos pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> obtegere.</note> all which time he ſpent in deſciding of their controuerſies: ſo diligent, as that <hi>Iethro</hi> his father in law did aduiſe him to ſlacke his diligence, and fauour himſelfe with more indulgence: this diligence is a duty which is required in Gouernours; <hi>hee that ruleth, let him doe it with diligence.</hi> The Lyon, ſaith <hi>Pierius,</hi> is the hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphicall figure of a Magiſtrate, which creature (ſome thinke) doth neuer take a ſound ſleepe, both becauſe in his deepeſt ſleepe, he alwayes moueth his tayle, and for that his eyes are alwaies open and neuer ſhut: which is the true por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture of a good Gouernour, whoſe head is filled with cares, while others ſleepe:<note place="margin">Maximinus.</note> which <hi>Maximinus</hi> well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, confirmed by his ſhort motto, <hi>(quo maior, hoc laborio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſior)</hi> the ſame wee finde in <hi>Homer,</hi> who ſaith, that publike Gouernours ought not to ſleepe all the night, much leſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Homerus Iliad <hi>2.</hi> Epaminondas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilo ut cives mei dormire poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſint.</p>
                     <p>Seneca. Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um domos illius vigilia defendit, omnium otium illius labor; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum delitias il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius induſtria, omnium vacati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem illius occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patio.</p>
                  </note> idle out all their dayes without ſome diligent employment.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Which thing <hi>Epaminondas</hi> well conſidered, who being asked why he watched in the night time, anſwered, that the citizens may ſleep. <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith of a diligent Gouernour, that his watchfulneſſe preſerueth men in their houſes, while they are aſleepe; his labour their caſe, his paines their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, his carefull obſeruation, their exemption from care: whoſe care how great it is wee may ſee in the example of <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, who reſigning vp the gouernement of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3387:20"/> 
                  <hi>Belgia</hi> to his ſonne <hi>Philip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">O ſili, magnum tibi on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>no, ego enim to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o tempore princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patus mei n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uam quadrantem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae magnis curis &amp; anxietatibus vacuum h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i.</note> ſpake with teares, trickling down his cheekes in this manner. O my deare ſonne, I haue now impoſed a great burthen vpon thee, in that I haue enioyned thee to gouerne this people, the weight of which burthen, I haue often felt; who during the whole time of my gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, could not enioy one quarter of an houre, wherein I was wholly free from care: the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> denounceth a heauy curſe againſt all them who doe the work s of the Lord negligently, of which number this of g uernment is one of the chiefeſt, which no man muſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect as <hi>Gallio</hi> did, if he reſpect the fauour of God. But we are to know that all diligent employment is not good: there is <hi>triplex negotium</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itioſum.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Odioſum.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtuoſum.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> a vitious, odious, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous employment.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Math 2.7.</note>1 <hi>Negotium vitioſum,</hi> a vitious employment, wherein men are diligent to doe miſchiefe, as <hi>Herod</hi> who was diligent in ſearching for Chriſt, that he might deſtroy him; this dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence is ſinfull.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Negotium odioſum,</hi> when men buſie themſelues in thoſe things which fall without the bounds and compaſſe of their calling. Let ſuch men know that hee who is buſie in other mens matters, neglecting or omitting their owne affaires, God will giue him as little thankes for his diligence, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> did <hi>Abſolon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam 15.2. 1 Pet 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> who off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to vndertake a needleſſe and thankeleſſe paines in his fathers office, who was ſeuerely puniſhed of God as a buſie body: this diligence is hatefull.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Negotium virtuoſum,</hi> a vertuous employment, when men are diligent in their functions whereunto God hath called them; the Miniſter in Preaching Gods word in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; the Ruler in hearing complaints, refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming abuſes, determining of controuerſies; this diligence is lawfull and vſefull, and thus was <hi>Moſes</hi> diligent.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 29.16.</note>
                  <hi>Iob</hi> is commended for this kind of diligence in his office; <hi>he ſought out the cauſe diligently:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Seneca. ad Lucil. epiſt. <hi>118.</hi> Non tam benignum &amp; liberale natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra nobis tempus dedit, ut aliquid ex illo vacet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</p>
                     <p>Ariſt. in Occon. experg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſcidecet prius dominum quam ſervum &amp; cubitum ire paſterius.</p>
                     <p>Facilius eſſe Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidi paſtoralem vitam egiſſe quam regalem. Aguanus in Pſ. <hi>Luke 18.4.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Domitian. Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae fuit deſidiae ut in cubiculo ſolus, acuto ſtilo muſcas confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geret. <hi>Prou. 24.31.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> let euery Ruler therfore reſolue vpon a painefu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l and diligent courſe no way foſtering idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he that hath the leaſt imployment in the world (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) hath no time left to ſpend in an idle manner, becauſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3387:20"/> nature hath not beſtowed on vs ſo much as whereof we can be prodigall. The Magiſtrates buſineſſe is more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and therefore it is expedient that he be an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good husband of time: that which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> requireth in a Maſter of a family, is no leſſe requiſite in a Ruler in the Common-wealth; that is, he muſt be the firſt vp in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and the laſt man in the euening; not preſuming that his preheminence can excuſe his diligence. <hi>Dauid</hi> was firſt a ſheepheard, and afterwards a Ruler; and his firſt kinde of life was leſſe laborious, the ſecond more induſtrious and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious: godly induſtry in this office, will remoue the ſhame and infamy of that iudge in the Goſpell; who becauſe hee would not be troubled, is therefore branded with iniuſtice; as alſo of that Romane Emperour <hi>Domitian,</hi> who would all the day long ſit in his chamber and kill flyes with ſharpe needles. Where there is a ſluggiſh Husband-man (ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>) the field will be ouergrowne with thornes; ſo where a ſluggiſh Gouernour, all things will be amiſſe and out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: he that is not fit to take paines in gouernment, is not fit for gouernment; as the poore woman to <hi>Adrian</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour (who denyed to take her petition, becauſe then hee had no leiſure to heare her) replyed, <hi>noli ergo imperare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Dionyſ. Caſſius. Bernard. de or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine vitae.</p>
                     <p>Moſes in ſilentio loquebatur, &amp; in otio operabatur. Ierom epiſt ad ruſticum mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chum: Facito ſemper aliquid operis, ut te dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolus inveniat occupatum. Dilectione. <hi>Exod. 32 32.</hi> Greg dele me <hi>1.</hi> Tolle me de hoc officio, ne ſim le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlator populi.</p>
                  </note> if you haue no leiſure, leaue your Empire: let therefore all Gouernours be exhorted to imitate <hi>Moſes</hi> in his diligence: whereof Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh thus, <hi>Moſes</hi> euen in his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence was a ſpeaker, and in his relaxation, he was a diligent labourer: and to remember the counſell of Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be thou idle, but alwaies diligent in ſome good buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſutable to thy calling, that Sathan may neuer finde thee but well employed.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Dilectione,</hi> by his affectionate loue towards them: when the people offended God, hee prayed vnto God for them in this manner: <hi>either pardon their ſinne, or elſe raze my name out of the booke of life:</hi> by which booke whether wee vnderſtand,</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Liber legiſlaturae,</hi> as Saint <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> blot mee out of the booke of Law-giuers and Rulers, diſmiſſe me from the office of iudicature.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:3387:21"/>
                  <note place="margin">Dimitte me de hac vita Vbi electi ad fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam gloriam conſcribuntur.</note>2 <hi>Liber viuentium in hac vita:</hi> that is, blot me out of the booke and catalogue of them who haue their being, liuing, and mouing in this life: or,</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Liber vitae aeternae:</hi> that is; raze my name out of that booke wherein the names of the elect are written.</p>
               <p>In what ſence ſoeuer we take it, wee cannot but diſcerne great loue in <hi>Moſes</hi> towards Gods people: wherein <hi>Moſes</hi> reſembleth a childe, who ſeeing his father about to turne out of doores one of his ſeruants whom he dearely affecteth, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat of his loue towards that ſeruant, hee thus ſaith to his father:<note place="margin">Pater noli hunc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ijce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, aut ſi cum eijcis, me queque eijcito.</note> Father, I humbly beſeech you caſt not out this your ſeruant whom I ſo heartily affect, as that I cannot lie comfortably, if I be depriued of his ſociety and company, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſo, turne me out of doores in his ſtead, or caſt me out with him:<note place="margin">Bernardus in Cont. ſerm. <hi>12.</hi> Si dives quiſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am mulieri pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perculae dicat, &amp;c.</note> or otherwiſe (as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith) he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth a poore woman, who comming very hungry to a rich mans doore, with her tender infant in her armes which ſhe dear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly loueth; the houſholder inuit th h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe and refreſh her ſelfe, but withall forbiddeth her to bring in her childe with her, leſt it make a noiſe and trouble the houſe: which mother refuſeth all the kindneſſe that is offered vnto her, becauſe her childe cannot partake thereof; ſhe had rather faſt and continue in hu ger, rather then that her childe ſhould be neglected and endangered. In like manner Iſrael was as a froward childe,<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Numb. 11 12.</hi> Exporta hunc populam in ſinu tuo, quemadin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum portat nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>icius lacten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</p>
                     <p>Praeſtat ut unus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>reat quam u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tas Bernard in ſeſto Mariae Magdal. Pene oblitus ſim Moſen ſacrili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoris huius rore perſuſum. <hi>Exod. 2.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> carried in the boſome of <hi>Moſes</hi> a tender nurſe, who had rather himſelfe be depriued of comfort then they, had rather periſh b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing but one man, then all they being ſo many: this was an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſymptome of his extraordinary loue. Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Saints who were annoynted with the oyle of charity, as of <hi>Paul,</hi> who wiſhed himſelfe anathematized for his brethren the Iewes: of <hi>Iob,</hi> who was <hi>(coeco oculus, &amp; claudo pes)</hi> an eye to the blinde, and a foote to the lam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: of <hi>Samuel,</hi> who lamented for <hi>Saul</hi> all the dayes of his life: of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who forg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tting his brethrens iniuries, louingly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth them: at the laſt he ſpeaketh of <hi>Moſes</hi> thus: <hi>I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forgot Moſes,</hi> who was throughly bewetted with the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we of charity towards Gods people, and that both before
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3387:21"/> he was in office when hee tooke part with the Hebrew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Egyptian, as alſo after that he was ſetled therein:<note place="margin">
                     <p>Bernar. in Cant. ſerm <hi>30.</hi> p. <hi>658.</hi> Ille renuit, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re? ob nimiam profecto dilectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, qua illi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo devinctus tenebatur; &amp; quontam non requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebat quod ſibi utile ſoret, ſed quod multis. <hi>Exod. 18 16. Deut. 16.18. Heathens.</hi> Nec heſperus nec lucifer ita lucet ſicut iuſtitia. Seneca. omnes virtutum ſpecies uno iuſtitiae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
                     <p>Seneca de ludo. Pietate &amp; iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia principes dij fiunt.</p>
                     <p>Idem de benifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cijs. Qui dat ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficia deos imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur, qui repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit foeneratores. Reiverius Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theolog.</p>
                     <p>Liberalitas ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur tantum ad bonum particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare, at iuſtitia ad bonum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>1 Kings 2.2.</hi> Fertitudo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertim in bello utilis, at iuſtitia &amp; in bello &amp; in pace.</p>
                  </note> wiſhing that by his ſmart and ſuffering, they might receiue eaſe and comfort: and the ſame Father vpon the <hi>Canticles,</hi> demanding the reaſon why <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo little reſpected his wealth and honour, as to leaue <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court; anſwereth, he refuſed to be called the ſonne of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his great loue wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>with he loued the people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, not ſeeking what might be profitable to himſelfe, but what might be comfortable vnto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>3 <hi>Iuſtitia,</hi> by doing of iuſtice among them.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithfull in this part of his office by his owne confeſſion; <hi>the people come vnto me when they haue any matter, and I iudge betweene one and another, according to the lawes and ordinances of God;</hi> one whereof is this, <hi>Iudges ſhalt thou make in all thy Cities, and they ſhall iudge the people with righteous iudgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This vertue of iuſtice is moſt highly commended.</p>
               <p n="1">1 By heathen Writers; no ſtarre to the heauens is ſo great an ornament, as iuſtice to a Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heſiod.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hac vnareges olim ſunt ſine creati,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dicere ius laeſis, iniuſta<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> tollere facta.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith that all kinde of vertues are comprehended within this of iuſtice, and that in a Commander it is a more needfull quality than any other whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Liberality</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a princely quality, and thereby (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) a man becomes like the Gods; yet iuſtice is better, becauſe whereas liberality extendeth onely to a particular good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſome few perſons, yet equity to a common good: and <hi>bonum quo communius còmelius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fortitude,</hi> another vertue beſeeming a Ruler, the which <hi>Dauid</hi> commendeth to <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne; <hi>be ſtrong and ſhew thy ſelfe a man:</hi> a man; firſt, in yeares no childe; ſecondly, in wiſedome no foole; thirdly, in courage no coward: yet iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice exceedeth it; for though fortitude is of abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty in the time of war, yet iuſtice is moſt neceſſary both in the time of war and peace.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:3387:22"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fathers.</hi> Auguſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de civitate dei. c. <hi>4.</hi> Remota iuſtitia, quid ſunt regna niſi magna la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trocinia.</p>
                     <p>Gregor. ad duos Franciae reges. Epiſtol. <hi>7. Prophets. Iſaiah. 1.17. Micah 6.8.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note>2 By the ancient fathers, Saint <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> take away iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice from a Kingdome, what is it but a harbour for all kind of villanies; and Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaith, <hi>(Summum in regibus bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſt iuſtitiam colere, &amp; ſubiectis non ſinere quod poteſtatis eſt, fieri, ſed quod aequum eſt cuſtodire:)</hi> that is, it is the excellency of Rulers to <hi>exerciſe iuſtice,</hi> and not to ſuffer men to doe what they deſire to doe, but compell them to that which they ought to doe.</p>
               <p n="3">3 By the holy Prophets of God, as <hi>Iſaiah: Seeke iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Micah: I will ſhew thee O man what the Lord requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of thee, ſurely to doe iuſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are foure ſorts of Gouernours who are in great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill to ſwerue from iuſtice, and ſo tranſgreſſe Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement herein.</p>
               <p>Men
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Fearefully minded.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Voluptuouſly diſpoſed.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Ambitiouſly qualified.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Couetouſly affected.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Timorous.</hi> Pilatus pluris faciebat impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris Romani, quam dei gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Heb. 11.27.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Timiditas iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu calamitas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentis.</p>
                     <p>Moſes agnus &amp; leo, agnus in dei populum, leo in Pharaonem. <hi>Volup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uous. Heb. 11.25.</hi> Philo. Non ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri quicquam da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat praeter tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum naturae ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium.</p>
                  </note>1 <hi>Fearefully minded; Pilate</hi> was drawne into that foule and iniurious act of condemning the Sonne of God, who did no ſinne, for feare of the Iewes; had he not beene timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, hee had not beene ſo vniuſt, ſo iniurious: but <hi>Moſes</hi> was free from this exorbitant feare: hee feared neither the whole multitude of Iſrael, before whoſe eyes hee brake to pieces that coſtly Idoll which they had reared and lately worſhipped; nor yet the fury of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that potent King: <hi>(he feared not the fierceneſſe of the King)</hi> but with boldneſſe and courage, threatned Gods ſeuerity againſt his cruelty; therefore we need not doubt but that he dealt iuſtly with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man, who feared no man.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Voluptuouſly diſpoſed,</hi> thoſe in place of authority, who doe loue pleaſures more then godlineſſe, that they may maintaine their delights, will forget vprightneſſe. But this Ruler <hi>Moſes</hi> did alienate himſelfe from pleaſures, preferring a penſiue before a pleaſant life; choſing rather to ſuffer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction with the people of God, <hi>then to enioy the pleaſures of Pharaohs profane Court. Philo</hi> ſaith, he did not pamper nature deliciouſly, but onely gaue it that allowance which was
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3387:22"/> neceſſary: as ſometimes he faſted miraculouſly,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Barrad. Itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar. Mira res ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſuit magis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiſſe affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gi cum populo He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braeo, quam ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma dignitatis i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunditate oble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctari.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ambitious. Exod 4.13.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> ſo hee was abſtinent ordinarily: how can we but conceiue him iuſt and a louer of equity, who did diuert his mind from the loue of pleaſure and vanity.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Ambitiouſly qualified;</hi> how farre from ambition <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was the hiſtory teſtifieth, who when as God called him to the office of gouernment, he requeſted the Lord to thinke vpon ſome other man, ſaying, <hi>Send O Lord I pray thee by him whom thou ſhouldeſt ſend;</hi> whom this was whom <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> wiſhed God to ſend in ſtead of himſelfe, there are diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent opinions.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Some doe thinke that <hi>Moſes</hi> would haue <hi>Aaron</hi> his elder brother ſent, as <hi>Lyranus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lyranus. Quia ſenior erat &amp; eloquentior.</note> becauſe hee was both more ancient and more eloquent.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Others doe thinke that the man whom <hi>Moſes</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be ſent was the M ſſias:<note place="margin">Tertullianus. Cyprianus. Rupertus. Recuſavit Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ut eo recuſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, mitteretur Meſſias.</note> as <hi>Tertullian Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertus,</hi> who ſaith thus; <hi>Moſes</hi> refuſed the gouernment of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with a deſire that the Meſſias himſelfe might go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne.</p>
               <p>We will not ſcan that queſtion too farre, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r whoſoeuer it was whom he would haue ſent, it is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt apparent that ambitiouſly he did not affect the place himſelfe:<note place="margin">
                     <p>Gregor. moral. lib. <hi>35.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi> Quia apud ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente humilis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>blatam protinus tanti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>egm inis gloriam nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</p>
                     <p>Auguſt. de civit. det cap. <hi>19.</hi> Locus ſuperior ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne quo populus rigi non poteſt et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> adminiſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia vt decet, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men indecenter app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>2 S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>. 15.4. 2 S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> 2.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> giueth the reaſon why he was loth to take the place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a moſt humble man, not deſirous of preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency or vaine glory; whoſe backwardneſſe though it bee not altogether iuſtifiable, yet the inference thence is warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; <hi>viz.</hi> that we ought not auidiouſly &amp; too greedily thirſt after promotion: which leſſon Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> teacheth, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority though it may be receiued, yet it muſt not be too ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gerly purſued: becauſe it is commonly ſeene, that thoſe who haue moſt deſired gouernment, haue leaſt deſerued it: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>Abſolon</hi> would God I were Iudge; yet ſee how well he deſerues it: the hiſtory relateth that he was firſt, an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, though no blemiſh or ſpeck vpon him outwardly, yet moſt filthy within: ſecondly, an inceſtuous adulterer euen with his owne fathers concubines: thirdly, a thiefe and robber, who ſtole away the hearts of his fathers ſubiects, who thereby was more iniurious then if he had taken trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3387:23"/> fourthly,<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>2 Sam. 15.31.</hi> Philo. <hi>39 7.</hi> de vita Moſis.</p>
                     <p>Aſſumpto prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipata non hoc e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, ſicut nonnul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li ſolent ut auge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſamiliant ſuam: unicum habebat propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum neceſſarium invare ſubditos, &amp; dictis factiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> eorum utilitati conſulere.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Couetous. Heb. 11.26.</hi> Philo. Non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in theſauros condidit.</p>
                     <p>Barrad. Itinerar. in terram ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim</p>
                  </note> a traytor, conſpiring with <hi>Achitophel,</hi> againſt his owne annointed Father: thus you ſee his fitneſſe, and withall his earneſtneſſe for gouernement. I could wiſh that men would leſſe deſire their owne eleuation, ſo ſhould wee heare leſſe complaint of iniuſtice and oppreſſion; the ſumme is this, <hi>Moſes</hi> was not ambitious of his office, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not iniurious therein, as <hi>Philo</hi> noteth. He tooke the gouernement (not as ſome doe) onely for the rayſing of their name and fame, but with this intent, <hi>viz.</hi> that hee might be a helper to the oppreſſed, and that he might ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe them for their owne good.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Couetouſly affected,</hi> we reade that couetouſneſſe is the roote of all euill, in a ſpeciall manner of iniuſtice: of which crime <hi>Moſes</hi> was not guilty; <hi>for hee eſteemed the rebuke of Chriſt, greater riches then the treaſures of Egypt. Philo</hi> ſheweth that <hi>Moſes</hi> was not auidous of gold or ſilu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r: who when as he had beene nouriſhed by <hi>Thermutis</hi> the daughter of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh;</hi> ſhe preſenting him vnto the King her father, reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting him to reſpect the childe; the King being willing to gratifie her <hi>(diadema ſuum capiti eius impoſuit)</hi> he put a dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme vpon his head, the which <hi>Moſes</hi> pulled off againe, caſt it vpon the ground, and trod it vnder foote: which <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> obſeruing, demanded of an Enchanter what this act of the childe did portend; he replyed, that hereby was ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified how that this Hebrew childe ſhould ouercome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, ſubdue it, and tread it vnder, and ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne and deſpiſe all worldly wealth: how contented a man <hi>Moſes</hi> was with a little,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.20.</note> appeareth in his returne out of the land of Midian into Egypt, in which he tooke nothing with him of all that which he had gotten in Midian by his painefull induſtry,<note place="margin">Quòd poſſeſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem rerum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducarum parum curabat.</note> but left it all behinde him, carrying one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him his wife, his ſonnes, and the rod of God in his hand, all which did ſignifie that hee little cared for riches: and therefore he which ſo much neglected the riches which he had, he would not be vniuſt to get ſuch riches as hee had not.</p>
               <p>So that <hi>Moſes</hi> being neither timorous, voluptuous, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious nor couetous, it is not likely that his dealing was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vniuſt or vnrighteous.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:3387:23"/>
               <p>Againſt this iuſtice of <hi>Moſes</hi> two things are obiected,<note place="margin">
                     <p n="1">
                        <hi>1</hi> Obiectio. Oecumenius in epiſt lud.</p>
                     <p>Satanas dixit, Moſen non eſſe dignum ſepultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. eo quòd iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtè occidiſſet Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptium, cum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> non in ſepulchro ſed in ſabulo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peliviſſet. Solut.</p>
                     <p>Aquinas 2a. 2ae. quaeſt. <hi>60.</hi> art. ult. Videtur Moſes occidiſſe Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tanquam ex inſpiratione di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina, auth rita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem adeptus.</p>
                     <p>Ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>an. in Exod. Moſes ex divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na electione ad liberandos He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braeos habebat a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ritatem vinduandi iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias, &amp; hoc ſcie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat per revela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem divinam. <hi>Act. 7.15.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2</hi> O'nectio <hi>Numb. 11.15.</hi> Sol.</p>
                     <p>Pelargus in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</p>
                     <p>Haec clauſula no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat exceſſum imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tientiae, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro quantumlibet ſummo.</p>
                     <p>Greg in paſtoral. Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gedin. loc. com. p. <hi>43.</hi> Etſi fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum ſalus nobis quaerenda eſt; non tamen cum animarum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrarum iactura, ipſam deſiderare debemus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Numb. 12.22.</hi> Muſculus. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes haeſitando peccavit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Numb. 20.12 Pſal 106.33.</hi> Muſculus Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus quoſdam du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitationis &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidentiae in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um oſtendit.</p>
                     <p>Pelargus in loc. Dubitanter pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram percutit, quaſi impoſſibile eſſet ex petra a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam prodire, pro tam incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</p>
                     <p>Stando non ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo.</p>
                     <p>Propter terram vilem au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um pretioſum non contemnitur, ſed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rum eligitur, &amp; terra relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur.</p>
                     <p>Boſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>quer. mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. melſuge, aculcum fuge.</p>
                     <p>Apes flores dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſugunt, her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>has amaras re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquunt. Senec. Ambroſ. Patres inſtruunt, non modo cum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, ſed etiam cum errant.</p>
                  </note>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 That he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alt vniuſtly with others.</item>
                     <item>2 That he dealt vniuſtly with himſelfe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Obiect.</hi> Vniuſt to others, he ſlue the Egyptian, hauing no authority: <hi>Oecumenius</hi> ſaith, that in the diſputation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Michael</hi> and the diuell, about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans argument was this; <hi>Moſes</hi> moſt vniuſtly ſlue a man, and when he had ſlaine him, did not put him decently in a ſepulchre, therefore his body was not worthy of buriall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This fact of <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſufficiently cleared from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice by that of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> who ſaith that he had warrant to doe it by diuine direction and inſpiration; God reuealing vnto him, that hee ſhould be the Iſraelites deliuerer, the which he thought that they had all known as he, <hi>viz. (that God had determined by his hand to giue that people deliuerance)</hi> whereof this Hebrew was one: in which conſideration this fact is freed from iniuſtice.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Obiect.</hi> Hee dealt vniuſtly with himſelfe, in entreating God to kill him that he might not behold his miſery: <hi>I pray thee kill me, that I may not behold my miſery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I finde none of the ancient writers to iuſtifie this wiſh of his. <hi>Pelargus</hi> ſaith, this ſpeech importeth that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was exceſſiuely unpatient, though otherwiſe a good man. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſpeaking of this wiſh, ſaith, <hi>in deumingratitudo ſumma eſt, malle non eſſe quam miſerum eſſe:</hi> great was <hi>Moſes</hi> h s ingratitude, who deſireth rather not to be at all, then to be miſerable. Wee ought ſaith <hi>Zegedin,</hi> to ſeeke our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns good and ſafety, but not with the hazard of our owne ſoules: we muſt not doe this euill to our ſelu s, though thereby we are ſure, that great good would redound vnto our brethren. We are to know therefore, that as <hi>Moſes</hi> fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in other things, <hi>viz.</hi> firſt in doubting of Gods promiſes, when he ſaid that he would giue them ſufficient food, (can all the fiſh of the ſea bee gathered together to ſuffice them) which <hi>Dauid</hi> calleth an vnaduiſed ſpeech: <hi>he ſpake vnaduiſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his lips:</hi> ſecondly, in not beleeuing God, promiſing him water out of the rocke: wherein (as ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi>) he bewrayeth by many ſignes his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouoting and diffidence: as,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:3387:24"/>1 In that he ſmote the rocke twice, whereas once had beene ſufficient, and as much as God commanded.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In that he did it, when the people requeſted it, not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately when God commanded it.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In that he did not ſmite that rocke whereunto God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected him, but ſome other, as ſome thinke.</p>
               <p n="4">4 In that he ſpake not to the rocke, as God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, but to the people.</p>
               <p n="5">5 In that hee ſpake both doubtfully and faintingly, as <hi>Muſculus</hi> obſerueth.</p>
               <p>So that he failing in this ſpeech, as in ſome other before, we muſt learne to imitate him and other the Saints in their ſtandings, not in their failings: the moſt godly men, who haue their moſt golden affections, haue alſo ſome droſſie and earthly cogitations; abhorre thou their droſſie earthli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but affect their golden godlineſſe. The beſt ſanctified man is like vnto the Bee, which hath both hony and ſting; the ſting of naughtineſſe, as well as the hony of godlineſſe; licke thou the hony, but ſhun the ſting: wherefore it will be thy wiſedome to imitate the Bees, which doe ſucke the ſweet flowers, but leaue the bitter hearbs. It is a good ſpeech of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the Saints doe inſtruct vs not onely when by a pious conuerſation they keepe the law, but alſo they admoniſh vs when by abberration they tranſgreſſe the law. Let Rulers learne from <hi>Moſes</hi> to bee iuſt to others, yet not vniuſt to themſelues.</p>
               <p>And now becauſe this vertue, Iuſtice, for which <hi>Moſes</hi> is commended, hath beene ſo highly aduanced by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, ancient Fathers, Prophets; practiſed by this ſo great a Iudge in Iſrael, notwithſtanding the obiections to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: and foraſmuch as nothing is well done, which is not done in a good manner, let vs conſider how and in what manner iuſtice muſt be exerciſed.</p>
               <p>To the exerciſe of iuſtice, fiue things are requiſite: for the manner, it muſt be,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Complete; ſecondly, Generall; thirdly, Voluntary; fourthly, Deliberate; fiftly, Stable.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Complete.</note>1 Complete, iuſtice is that which hath theſe two
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3387:24"/> compounds,
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Mercy.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <p>Cyprian Oporte: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>dicem cum iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae aculco mel clementiae habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re commixtum. <hi>Mercy.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Prou. 10.18. Numb. 12.3.</hi> Deus vindictae gladium olco mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordiae acu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t.</p>
                        </note>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Seuerity.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Mercy: Salomon</hi> declareth the neceſſity of mercy in a man of authority; <hi>mercy and truth doe preſerue the King, and his throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed with mercy:</hi> in the booke of <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> we reade that <hi>Moſes was a very meeke man, aboue all the men that were vpon the earth.</hi> Let all godly Gouernours learne mercy from <hi>Moſes,</hi> yea from God himſelfe, who alwaies ſleepes the ſword of his ſeuerity, in the oyle of his mercy. Learne you to be mercifull, as your heauenly father is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Seuerity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seuerity.</note> which is as neceſſary as the former; for which purpoſe God hath put a ſword into his hand, that hee may exerciſe ſeuerity: in which act three things are conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Obiect,</hi> vpon whom it muſt be exerciſed.<note place="margin">Obiect.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Time,</hi> when it muſt be exerciſed.</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Cauſes,</hi> wherefore it muſt be exerciſed.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1 The Obiect of <hi>Seuerity,</hi> are offenders; who becauſe they are not all alike, nor of one ranke, you muſt therefore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them in their puniſhments. Some there are which offend of infirmity, and erre in ſimplicity: againſt ſuch,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.24.</note> you that are Gods terreſtriall Cherubims in this Engliſh Eden, muſt onely ſhake the ſword, for that is ſufficient.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou. 26.3.</hi> Flagellum equo, frenum aſino, virga ſtolido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tergo.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Others there are of a higher ranke then the former, being both ſtout and bold offenders; for whoſe mouthes there muſt be prepared Bits, for whoſe hand, Manacles; for whoſe feet, Stockes; and for whoſe backes Rods; as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> intimateth.</p>
               <p>I may not preſume to giue directions to your wiſedomes how to proportion your ſeuerity to the ſeuerall crimes you ſhall meet with; whether robberie, murther, or the like. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giue me leaue to be your Remembrancer concerning the Popes bloud-hounds, Prieſts and Ieſuites; who plot and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triue the death of Kings and Princes, the ruine and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of whole Kingdomes: aiming not at angles, acres, cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, and widdowes houſes, with <hi>Ahab,</hi> and the Phariſees, but at Kings Pallaces, whole countries: bloudy Butchers,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3387:25"/> who will not foule their hands with the blood of beaſts but of men, and that not in the blood of baſe abiects as <hi>Ahab</hi> in <hi>Naboths,</hi> but in the royall blood of Kings &amp; princes; theſe foxes muſt be hunted, diſcouered, worried, who if they bee not deſtroyed, will deſtroy our vineyard: O ſmite them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, becauſe they doe but watch a time to ſmite vs mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Time.</note>2 The time when it muſt exerciſed; when no warning will ſerue, nor eaſier meanes p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euaile: when as the bench hath giuen the malefactor both a diſcharge (goe thy way) and charge (ſinne no more) if he ſtill iterat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his offence, who can pitty him if puniſhment ouertake him:<note place="margin">Improbe Neptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num accuſat, qui iterûm naufra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acit.</note> he that wil needs to Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when once already he hath ſuffered ſhipwrack, if he fall foul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſecond time, hee may thanke himſelfe: if the axe of iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce hath beene laid vnto the roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of a naughty tree, two or three ſeſſions t gether, and ſtill ſhall bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g forth bitter fruit, diſhonourable vnto God, and da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us to the Common-wealth; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at remedy if this tree bee hewen downe by the axe of iuſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e (this being conſidered) that he who ſpareth the bad,<note place="margin">Bonis nocet qui malis parcit. <hi>Exod. 4.6.</hi> Magdeburgen. Centur. <hi>4.</hi> c <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>190.</hi>
                  </note> hee iniureth the good, and himſelfe moſt of all. The hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> when as it was ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tched out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was whole and ſound, but when he withdrew it a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld it in his boſome, it was leprous; which giu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th vs to vnderſtand, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s for a Ruler to puniſh and exerciſe ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty when there is cauſe, will be commodious vnto him; ſo to vſe conniuency, is very perilous.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cauſes.</note>Foure cauſes wherefore it muſt bee exerciſed: there is great cauſe why ſeuerity ſhould bee exerciſed, in regard of 1 <hi>God,</hi> 2 <hi>Gouernment,</hi> 3 <hi>Spectators,</hi> 4 <hi>Malefactors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.9.</note>1 Of God, that his wrath may be appeaſed. So long as <hi>Sauls</hi> ſinne went vnpuniſhed God was grieued but his ſonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s being hanged, he was appeaſed: God ſent a plague vpon Iſrael becauſe they tollerated open adulterers to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate their filthineſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal 106.30.</note> but ſo ſoone as <hi>Phineas</hi> executed iudgement, the plague was ſtayed.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Of the Gouernment, that it may be eſtabliſhed ſo ſaith <hi>Salomon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 4.25.</note> Take away the droſſe from the ſiluer, and behold a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3387:25"/> veſſell for the finer, take away the wicked from the King, and his throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Of the Spectators;<note place="margin">Deut. 21.11.</note> that they may bee cautioned and admoniſhed by their ſurveigh of others puniſhed.<note place="margin">In ſanguine tuo caeteri diſcent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedientiam. Poena ad paucos, metus ad omnes.</note> We read of a malefactor who deſiring pardon of the Iudge for his fact, he denied him, giuing this reaſon; by thy puniſhment others will learne amendment: puniſhment being like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a thunderbolt, the ſmart whereof though ſome few feele, yet all doe feare.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Of the Malefactors; that they may be bettered and ſo bleſſed: the theefe in the Goſpell had not died ſo penitently had he not died ſo painfully.<note place="margin">Metior eſt modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca amaritudo in fancibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quam ſupplicium aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in viſceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> It was good for <hi>Dauid</hi> that for his folly he was afflicted, and much good redoundeth vnto the malefactors when they are in this life puniſhed; it is better to ſuffer a ſhort though ſharp puniſhment here, then euerlaſting torment hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2</hi> Iuſtice generall.<note place="margin">Generall.</note>
               </head>
               <p>Generall iuſtice is that which reſpecteth all, rewarding the meaneſt in well doing, puniſhing the greateſt in euill doing: the which will caſhiere from the ſeat of iuſtice their ſeuerall vices.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, all reſpecting of perſons;<note place="margin">Exuat perſonam iudicis, qui in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit amici.</note> ſuch a Ruler holdeth on his courſe of iuſtice, though ſuperiours frowne, equals murmur and inferiours repine: he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth veritie, not petigree.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, all bribing and vnder-hand-gifting; it appeareth by <hi>Dauids</hi> ſpeech in the Pſalmes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.10.</note> how he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that the ſoules of all bribing Iudges dying without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance were in hell;<note place="margin">Dextra plena muneribus.</note> he wiſhing that his ſoule might not be with theirs; <hi>Gather not my ſoule with theirs, whoſe hands are full of gifts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All gifts and rewards are not vnwarrantable.</p>
               <p>There are,</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Munera honoris,</hi> gifts of honour;<note place="margin">1 Kings 10.2.</note> ſuch as the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> gaue to <hi>Salomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Munera amoris,</hi> gifts of loue;<note place="margin">Gen. 33.9.</note> ſuch as <hi>Iacob</hi> gaue vnto <hi>Eſau.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:3387:26"/>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 8 10.</note>3 <hi>Munera gratitudinis,</hi> gifts of thankfulneſſe; ſuch as <hi>Toi</hi> the King of <hi>Hamath</hi> ſent vnto <hi>Dauid; viz.</hi> veſſells of gold and ſiluer to congratulate his victories.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">Quae in fia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m malam &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; accipiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Muſcul.</note>4 <hi>Munera corruptionis,</hi> gifts of corruption; which are both tendred and receiued with an euill intent; namely to diuert the ſtreame of iuſtice: theſe gifts are vnallowable and damnable.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> all fearefulneſſe, terrour, and affrighting by ſuperiours:<note place="margin">Timiditas iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis eſt calamitas innocentis.</note> a godly Ruler muſt remember that the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity of the Gouernour, is the calamity of the inferiour: whereas this generall iuſtice inableth a Iudge to doe iuſtice to all equally without reſpect of any; without hope of gifts from any, and without feare of any whomſoeuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">Voluntary.</note>
                  <hi>3</hi> Iuſtice voluntary.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>1 Pet. 5.2.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>2 Chron. 24.6. Exod. 30.14.</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t non eſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarius guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator quem cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piditas trahit, ita nec ſpontane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us quem timor urget.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>2 Kings 12.5.</hi> Gorravij. cuncta opera religionis debent eſſe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntaria. <hi>Deliberate. Prou. 18.31.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note>Gouernours in the Church are bound to performe their offices, not coactiuely, but willingly; ſo muſt all Rulers that are appointed to doe iuſtice in the Common-wealth. <hi>Iehoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ada</hi> did that which was iuſt in cauſing the people to bring offrings vnto the Lord, wherwith the Temple was repaired, but herein his iuſtice was blemiſhed, in that he did it not vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, by or of himſelfe (for during the ſpace of 23. yeers, the breaches of the Temple were not repaired) but coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely, being conſtrained thereunto by the ſtrict iniunction and mandate of good King <hi>Ioaſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As he is not a iuſt iudge whom couetouſneſſe draweth, no more is he a voluntary Ruler, whom feare conſtraineth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>4</hi> Iuſtice deliberate.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He who anſwereth a matter before he heare it, it is folly and ſhame vnto him</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) the want of deliberation in the execution of iuſtice, is diſallowed of all ſorts of men; as,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 7.51.</note>1 By the Iewes: <hi>Nichodemus</hi> ſaith, that it was not the manner of the Iewes to iudge a man ere he were heard.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By the <hi>Romans; Paul</hi> ſaith, it is not the cuſtome of the Romans to deliuer any man to death,<note place="margin">Acts 25.10.</note> till the accuſer come face to face, and that the priſoner haue liberty to make his defence.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:3387:26"/>3 By Heathens: <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Seneca. Qui ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit aliquid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>audita altera parte, aequum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet ſtatuerit, haud aequus fuit.</note> he that cenſureth and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth not, ſuppoſe his ſentence be iuſt, yet himſelfe is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt: wherefore it is moſt needfull, that the cauſe be well conſidered, ere the iudgement be pronounced, becauſe the ſentence once paſſed, cannot conueniently be recalled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>5</hi> Iuſtice Stable.<note place="margin">Stable.</note>
               </head>
               <p>He who will be reſpected in his Magiſtracy,<note place="margin">Levitas eſt mobilitas animi, qua homines levi de cauſa mentes vel ſermones fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile mutant.</note> muſt auoid lenity, which is a flexibility of minde, whereby men are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily drawne to alter their mindes, words and actions, vpon any ſmall or no cauſe. A Iudge muſt not be like the vulgar Iewes, who this day would deifie, and to morrow crucifie the ſame man; nor yet like vnto <hi>Pilate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iiſdem labijs Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum miſit ad crucem, quibus cum pronuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verat innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note> who commanded Chriſt to the Croſſe, with thoſe ſame lips, with which he pronounced him innocent: but he muſt be like the needle toucht with the Load ſtone of conſtancy, euer looking one way, or like the Egyptian Pyramis, vpon which was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>(nec flatu nec fluctu)</hi> neither windes nor flouds ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue me.</p>
               <p>So that it largely and plainely appeareth, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithfull as to God, to <hi>Aaron,</hi> ſo to the people ouer whom he was Gouernour, as is euident by theſe three particulars of his diligence, loue, and iuſtice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>3 Generall Obſeruation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obſeruation.</note> Thoſe that are in Moſes place, muſt be faithfull as Moſes was.</head>
               <p>The truth of this Theſis, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinths,</hi> in theſe words,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.2.</note> 
                  <hi>it is required of diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, that euery man be found faithfull:</hi> and for a patterne wee can finde no man more fit then <hi>Moſes:</hi> who in all the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the houſe, was a faithfull Monitor: in all the wants and neceſſities of the houſe, was a faithfull ſupplier: in all the controuerſies of the houſe, a faithfull determiner, and in all the guidance and ordering of the houſe, a moſt faithfull Gouernour.</p>
               <p>Reaſons are two, drawne
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>A Pari.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>A Periculo.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:3387:27"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 1 <hi>A pari,</hi> fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thfulneſſe is required in perſons that haue leſſe power then Magiſtrates, as in</p>
               <p n="1">1 Gouernours of priuate families: <hi>thoſe ſeruants that haue beleeuing maſters, let them doe them ſeruice, becauſe they (that is) their maſters are faithfull vnto them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6 2.</note> giuing them thei al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance both ſeaſonably and fully.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 22.14.</note>2 Seruants: <hi>Abimelech</hi> conceiueth <hi>Dauid</hi> to bee a fit ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant for <hi>Saul,</hi> becauſe he was a faithfull man.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 1.6.</note>3 Children, hau ng faithf ll children.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 13.17. Prou. 14.5.</note>4 Meſſengers, a faithfull Meſſe ger preſerueth.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Witneſſes, who muſt ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the truth, and nothing but the truth.</p>
               <p>If therefore faithfulneſſe be requiſite in Gouernours, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, Children, Witneſſes; all of them being of an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke; it is as much, if not more neceſſary in Rulers, whom God hath ſet in a place tranſcendent.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> 2 <hi>A periculo,</hi> it is a caſe very dangerous and hurtfull, to be a Magiſtrate, and not to be faithfull: it will be hurtfull two waies.</p>
               <p n="1">1 To them that are inferiour: inferiours will eye and imitate thoſe that are in higher place. The courſe of nature will ſooner faile (ſaith <hi>Caſſiodorus</hi>) then the people leaue off to aſſimulate their Rulers:<note place="margin">Caſsiodor. Fulgentius ad Theodoret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Senatorem ep. <hi>6.</hi> qui in ſeculi cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine conſtituti ſunt, aut multos ad ſalutem du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt, aut pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos ſecum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt. <hi>1. Iſaiah. 21.23.</hi>
                  </note> as the head is affected, ſo moſt commonly the whole body. If the Gouernour who is the head, be vnfaithfull, he makes many moe vnfaithfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides himſelfe: this is plainely laid downe by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in his firſt chapter, who when as hee had ſaid in the 21. verſe, <hi>that the faithfull Citie was become an harlot;</hi> hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the reaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n thereof in the 23. verſe, <hi>viz. their iudges were vnfaithfull.</hi> The Citizens of Ieruſalem did euidently diſcerne their Iudges vnfaithfull ſitting on the ſeate of iuſtice, and therefore they reſolue to be as vnfaithfull in their courſe of merchandize.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To himſelfe, that is, the Gouernour: for if a Seruant, a Meſſenger, Witneſſe, or Child, that is vnfaithfull, cannot auoide and eſcape the puniſhment of vnfaithfulneſſe; how ſhall Magiſtrates eſcape, whoſe vnfaithfulneſſe extendeth much farther?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:3387:27"/>
               <head>The fourth Generall is the Application.</head>
               <p>Wherein I humbly craue leaue that I may apply it;</p>
               <p n="1">1 To you the Honourable Iudges,<note place="margin">Iudges.</note> in whom God and the King hath repoſed ſuch truſt, as (at this time) to giue you the power <hi>oyer et terminer,</hi> to heare and determine thoſe cauſes and ſuits, as alſo to helpe and reforme thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grieuances with which you ſhall meete within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of theſe eight Counties: that you will be well pleaſed to take <hi>Moſes</hi> his faithfulneſſe into your conſideration, and to let him be your preſident in the exerciſe of your functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. O let his ſcience direct you, his conſcience prouoke you to faithfulneſſe: towards God by your pious and zealous deportment;<note place="margin">Plant. Ne officij veſtri ſatis memores, immemores ſace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re videar. <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
                  </note> towards Gods Miniſters embracing and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing ſuch as are painefull and peaceable; and towards Gods people, which you ſhall teſtifie both by your diligence for them, and your loue towards them, eſpecially by doing of iuſtice among them, according to the aforeſaid rules of iuſtice, which I haue ſo much the more inlarged,<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Councellors.</hi> Baſil in cap. <hi>1.</hi> Iſ. Intollerabile eſt ſuperbiae argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare ſe nullius egere conſilio. Egardus. Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam defenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das ſuſcipiat cauſas quas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit eſſe malas. Solon. Conſulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da non quae ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſima ſed quae optima.</p>
                     <p>Gregor. Turpe eſt defendere quod non mihi conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit eſſe aequum. Papian. Non tam facile eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſare fraticidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quam facere. <hi>Exod. 23.2.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> by how much I know that it is moſt neceſſarily required towards the ſupportance of your faithfulneſſe. But leſt I make you ſeeme vnmindfull of your duty by preſſing it too farre, and vrging it too long, I will end it with <hi>Dauids</hi> ſhort exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>loue innocency, and the thing that is right; for this ſhall bring you peace at the laſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 To you the learned Counſellors, whoſe calling euery intelligent man will acknowledge both vſefull and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that you blemiſh not your worthy profeſſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1 By vndertaking and countenancing ſuch cauſes as are naught. <hi>Solons</hi> aduiſe was, that men ſhould counſell rather things wholeſome, then meerely delightſome. Saint <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſaith, it is a vile part to vndertake the defence of that which in it ſelfe is not honeſt. We reade of <hi>Papian</hi> the Oratour, who being requeſted by <hi>Antonius Caracalla</hi> the Emperour, to defend the fratricide of his brother <hi>Geta,</hi> replied: it is more eaſie to commit it, then to defend it: the Lord himſelfe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a law ſtraitly againſt it, <hi>thou ſhalt not ſpeake in a cauſe to wreſt iudgement;</hi> and menaceth a curſe againſt ſuch as pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it; <hi>woe to them that call euill good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:3387:28"/>2 By imparting the ſecret paſſages of your Clients cauſe, and his intended proceedings vnto his aduerſary, againſt which branch of vnfaithfulneſſe, call to minde that ſpeech of the Poet in another caſe:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Ovid.</note>Eximia eſt virtus praeſtare ſilentia rebus:</l>
                     <l>At contra grauis eſt culpa, tacenda loqui.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Prou 11.13.</note>But eſpecially that of <hi>Salomon, hee that is of a faithfull heart, concealeth a matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 By being vnſtable and fickle in your counſels; againſt which ſort of counſellors,<note place="margin">Saluſtius ad Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarem. Qui huc illuc fluctuantes agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur.</note> 
                  <hi>Saluſt</hi> bitterly inueieth: you ſhall make your faculty ridiculous, while you are ſo various and inconſtant in your opinions, denying that to be no law this Terme, which you auoued to be law the laſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4 By defiling your hands, ſoules, and conſciences with gifts and bribes, which hinder iuſt proceedings; whereas you ought to loue verity more then opulency; and to learne euen from <hi>Balaam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aegard. Magis apud vos valeat amor veri quam lucri. <hi>Miniſters. 1 Cor. 4.2.</hi>
                  </note> thus much fidelity; as not for a houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, much leſſe for a purſefull or handfull of ſiluer, to doe that which is vniuſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 To you my brethren in the miniſtry (to whom I will ſpeake the leſſe, becauſe you are the leaſt number in this worthy auditory) that you be found faithfull according to the Apoſtles iniunction: To fulfill which aright, our care muſt be to ſhun ſuch things as hinder it, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 Idleneſſe, God hauing ſet vs in his vineyard, the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt being great, we muſt beſtirre our ſelues, alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that ſpeech of Saint <hi>Paul: Woe vnto me if I preach not the Goſpell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.11.</note>2 Vaine glory: a faithfull Miniſter, will not Preach him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">Proſper. de vit. contemp. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> but Chriſt: hee will ſo ſpeake, that in all things God may be glorified, not intending to draw from the people <hi>(plauſum, ſed gemitum.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.33.</note>3 Couetouſneſſe: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth vs by his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, not to ſeeke altogether our own profit, but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of many, that they might be ſaued.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">Iurors.</note>4 To you the worthy Iurors, who are ſworne to deale faithfully betwixt the King and his Subiects, the Plaintiffe and Defendant: let it be your care to proceed according to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3387:28"/> euidence and Conſcience. Forget not your oath,<note place="margin">Secundum acta &amp; probata. Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaeus de ſtatibus</note> which is to deale impartially, without all reſpect of perſons, either for feare or affection, which oath is of an aſtringent nature: <hi>he that ſweares an oath to binde himſelfe by a bond,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 30.3.</note> 
                  <hi>hee ſhall not breake it, but ſhall doe according to all that proceedeth out of his mouth:</hi> be not you of the number of thoſe Iurors, who are reſolued of their verdict, ere the euidence be produced, or the cauſe opened, and are ſo ſtiffely made in or againſt the cauſe, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey cannot be diuerted; but tread ye in the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den path of truth and equity, reſolue with conſtancy to continue therein, and whoſoeuer ſhall vſe meanes to turne you out of that way, anſwere them with <hi>Iephtah:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudges 11.25.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue ſworne, I cannot goe backe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 To you the Officers of the County; I meane,<note place="margin">Officers.</note> Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Bailiff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and the like; who are taken in to further iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: be aduiſed to deale faithfully. Be not you ſo dimme ſighted, and wilfully ignorant, as that you cannot attach a party, while he is both preſent, as alſo your Writ extant. You know with what intent <hi>Ionathan</hi> carried his arrowes into the field; not to hit or hurt his friend,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 20.22.</note> but to ſafeguard him, and admoniſh him to be gone <hi>(goe thy way)</hi> vſe not you your Writs in that kinde, as he his arrowes; aduiſe not men to be gone, when you ſhould ſummon them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: but be faithfull in that office which you haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken. Concerning which perſons, there is alſo required the care of you the Iuſtices, that if you finde any one of theſe Officers, by his <hi>(non eſt inuentus)</hi> to abuſe the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; that you thruſt him out, and ſet another Officer in his place, who will deale more faithfully.</p>
               <p n="6">6 To you the truſty Witneſſes,<note place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> vpon whoſe teſtimony dependeth the iſſue of euery cauſe, that you may bee wary and well aduiſed what you ſpeake, that nothing proceed from you but truth. <hi>Salomon</hi> maketh a ſhort,<note place="margin">Prou. 14.5.</note> yet a perfect deſcription of a faithfull witneſſe; <hi>a faithfull witneſſe will not lye:</hi> the vnfaithfulneſſe of a witneſſe, is to ſpeake that which is falſe, the which is flatly forbidden in <hi>Exodus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20. Exod. 23.1.</note> 
                  <hi>thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe:</hi> and againe, <hi>thou ſhalt not put thine hand with the wicked, to be an vnrighteous Witneſſe.</hi> Remember I
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3387:29"/> pray you that he who by oath giueth in falſe euidence, ſhall finde a threefold inconuenience.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Committit culpam,</hi> he offendeth heinouſly, he ſinneth exceedingly, falleth fouly: if a ſinne to ſpeake falſly, how great a ſinne to ſweare falſly? a falſe Witneſſe ſaith <hi>Iſiodor,</hi> offendeth three wayes:</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Iſidor. de ſammo bono lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>1 <hi>In Deum,</hi> againſt God, <hi>cuius veritatem annihilat:</hi> whoſe truth he would nullifie.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>In iudicem cuius iudicium perturbat,</hi> he is offenſiue to the Iudge, cauſing him to doe iniuſtice againſt his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and reſolution.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>In accuſatum, quem ſuo teſtimonio condemnat:</hi> hee is iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to the accuſed, whoſe innocency he ouerthroweth by his falſe teſtimony.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Greg. Qui ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum teſtimonium dixerunt, nulla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus ad teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium ſunt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittendi, quia infames ſunt, &amp; iuſte repellendi. Omnis qui fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum teſtimon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um dicit contra proximum ſuum dignus eſt ut ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ciatur. <hi>Deut. 19 19. Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 21 28.</hi> Pantheologia Reguem. p. <hi>1101. Pſal. 15.3. All.</hi>
                  </note>2 <hi>Amittit famam,</hi> he loſeth his reputation, in ſuch ſort, as that euer after he cannot be reſpected or credited.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Incurrit poenam:</hi> hee bringeth vpon himſelfe, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments both temporall and eternall.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Temporall: the ancient Iewes did ſo abhorre falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, as that they cauſed them to be torne in pieces with Dogs. The Lord in the booke of <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> deſcribeth the puniſhment of the falſe Witneſſe: <hi>you ſhall doe vnto him as he thought to haue done vnto his brother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Eternall, <hi>a falſe Witneſſe ſhall periſh,</hi> viz. <hi>aeternaliter. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſaith <hi>that ſuch ſhall not enter into Gods heauenly Tabernacle, but ſhall come to vtter deſtruction,</hi> Pſal. 5.6. <hi>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les omnes qui lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur mendacium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 To you all: that counſell which our Sauiour gaue to all, as touching watchfulneſſe, the ſame I giue to you all concerning faithfulneſſe, <hi>be faithfull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſtly, to the end that all you may be prouoked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to faithfulneſſe, hearken vnto ſome ſhort motiues which are added in the concluſion: theſe are foure in number.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Preſidence. 1 Theſſ. 5.24.</note>1 Gods preſidence; 2 Gods obſeruance; 3 Gods indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; 4 Gods recompence.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Gods preſidence: God the Father who hath called vs, he is faithfull; ſo Chriſt Ieſus our bleſſed Sauiour, he is an abſolute patterne of faithfulneſſe farre aboue <hi>Moſes,</hi> a more
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3387:29"/> faithfull Prophet then he, <hi>for he taught all things:</hi> a more faithfull Prieſt then he; <hi>for he offered vp himſelfe for the ſinnes of the people:</hi> a more faithfull Iudge then he, <hi>for he will render to euery man according to his workes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obſeruance.</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>etius. Mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a eſt n ceſſi as probitatis, cum agit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s ante oculo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> iudicis cuncta ceruentis.</p>
                     <p>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dentius. Quicquilag, ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tim palamve, memento inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatorem ſemper adeſſe Deum. Hic intuitus ſammi reg, ante oculos me itis propoſitus ad omne bonum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at.</p>
                     <p>Lens moleſtior eſt in facie, quam vel que corporis maculae: ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> exigua pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta in ejus vita pro magnis ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur quia vita ejus omnibus conſpicua.</p>
                     <p>Livius Druſ. Quo cives uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſint qua ratione utar vitae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendae. <hi>Indulgence.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Gods obſeruance: God narrowly obſerueth their courſe, and theref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re they had neede to keepe compaſſe: ſo ſaith <hi>Salomon: if there be oppreſſion, vniuſtice, or vnfaithfulneſſe in a Citie, he that is higher then the higheſt, obſerueth:</hi> who will not walke warily (ſaith <hi>Boetius</hi>) that is in the ſight of the Iudge continually. The counſell which <hi>Prudentius</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth is very wholeſome, <hi>viz.</hi> whatſoeuer thou doſt openly or ſecretly, remember that God beholds thee, and then thou wilt performe thy worke faithfully: Whereunto let me adde the obſeruance of men; a Iudge or Gouernour is as the face in the body: which as it is of all parts of the body moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, ſo a Wen, a Wart, or Spot vpon it, is not endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe of euery man it is eaſily diſcerned and eſpyed Let the Magiſtrate walke circumſpectly, becauſe he walketh viſibly. <hi>Liuius Druſus</hi> the Tribune, who dwelling in a low cottage, not diſcernable by any paſſenger; and a Carpenter making him an offer, that for fiue Talents of ſiluer, he would raiſe it vp higher, and make it moſt conſpicuous: he repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I would giue thee as much more as thou askeſt of me, if thou couldeſt turne the inſide of my houſe outward, to the end that all the Citizens might ſee how faithfully and iuſtly I doe deport my ſelfe in my priuate family. Therefore let your ſtudy and care be to walke ſo vprightly, as that you neede not be terrified or deiected at Gods or mans obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancy.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Gods indulgence: how euer a man be defectiue in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, yet if he be ſincerely faithfull, God couereth and pardoneth all his infirmities, not excepting either againſt the perſon or action of that man in whom he findeth a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart. Example hereof wee haue in <hi>Iudah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſea 11.12.</note> wh f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r her ſinnes deſerued to be reiected of God, yet becauſe <hi>ſhee ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with God, and was faithfull to the Saints,</hi> that is, when ſhee ruled, ſhe was faithfully affected, therefore ſhe was beloued and commended of God: that man may bee certaine of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3387:30"/> Gods fauourable indulgement, who hath a care of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deportment.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">Recompence.</note>4 Gods recompence and reward of faithfulneſſe, both here and hereafter.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Here in this life; they that are faithfull, ſhall hereby ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a good report among men: there are a ſort of men (ſaith Saint <hi>Iude</hi>) who will be ſpeaking euill of them that be in gouernement.<note place="margin">Iude 8.</note> Now what a happineſſe is it to a Ruler, that his enemies cannot ſpeake of him as of an euill doer; cannot iuſtly accuſe him, cannot blemiſh him. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> had many enemies who ſought an aduantage,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan. 6.4.</hi> Nullam occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem potuerunt invenire propte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea quòd fidus eſſet.</note> or ſome iuſt occaſion againſt him: <hi>yet ſo faithfull was he</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>that they could finde no fault in him:</hi> the name of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall be honoured to the worlds end, becauſe hee was found faithfull: neither ſhall ſuch a man obtaine and retaine onely a good name, which is to be prized aboue gold and ſiluer, but all other temporall bleſſings:<note place="margin">Prou. 28.20.</note> the faithfull man ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with bleſſings.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In the life to come; God doth recompence it with eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory. Our Sauiour ſhall ſay to all ſuch as are faithfull at the day of iudgement: <hi>Come thou good and faithfull ſeruant; becauſe thou haſt beene faithfull in a little, I will make thee Ruler ouer much, enter thou into thy Maſters ioy:</hi> which bleſſing is promiſed to the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 2.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>be thou faithfull vnto death, and I will giue thee the crowne of life:</hi> for which life the Lord fit vs all; and vnto which the Lord bring vs all in his owne appointed time, and that for Chriſt Ieſus his ſake, his onely Sonne, our bleſſed Sauiour, to whom with the Father and the holy Spirit be glory, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3387:30"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
